<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A touch-stone to try (by our knowledge, belief, and life) whether we be Christians in name onely, or Christians in deed. Or, The character of a true beleever, that walks in some measure answerable to the gospell, his Christian profession, and the millions of mercies he hath received. / By R.Y. of Roxwell in Essex.</title>
            <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y193B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1150_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208624</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867557</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867557</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119873</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 165:E1150[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A touch-stone to try (by our knowledge, belief, and life) whether we be Christians in name onely, or Christians in deed. Or, The character of a true beleever, that walks in some measure answerable to the gospell, his Christian profession, and the millions of mercies he hath received. / By R.Y. of Roxwell in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10, A-V, 11-30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>and are to be sold by Andrew Crooke, at the signe of the Greene Dragon in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.Y = Richard Younge.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 20th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119873:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Touch-Stone To try (by our knowledge, belief, and life) whether we be Chriſtians in name onely, or Chriſtians in deed. OR, The Character of a true Beleever, that walks in ſome meaſure anſwerable to the Goſpell, his Chriſtian profeſſion, and the millions of mercies he hath received. By <hi>R. Y.</hi> of <hi>Roxwell</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 13.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Examine your ſelves whether ye be in the faith: prove your owne ſelves. Know ye not your owne ſelves, how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you, except ye be reprobates?</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Andrew Crooke,</hi> at the ſigne of the Greene Dragon in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:119873:2"/>
            <p>I Have peruſed this Treatiſe, and approving it to be very pithy, pious, and profitable, I allow it to be printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>THe Reader may think it ſtrange that the Proofes are not alleadged, but they were found to be ſo many in number, that the very pointing to them would have taken up neere as much roome as the matter it ſelfe, and ſo have doubled the charge; which (in that they are moſtly to be given away) could not be afforded: Beſides, few uſe to turn to every Scripture; and every ſanctified heart is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon all that is herein delivered.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119873:2"/>
               <head>The CHARACTER of a true Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, &amp;c. in reading whereof reflect upon your ſelves, and ſee what compariſon there is between that you are, and what you ſhould be: and then with bleſſing from above, it will much further you in your way to Heaven: for therefore are we Chriſtians in name onely, becauſe we think our ſelves Chriſtians indeed, and already good enough.</head>
               <p>§. 1. <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> True Beleever is one, that God (of his free grace and good pleaſure) hath choſen, and elected to eternall life before the foundation of the World: and whom Chriſt hath redeemed with his precious bloud.</p>
               <p>§. 2. He is effectually called, and become a new Creature by regeneration, being both begotten and borne a new of God by the immortall ſeed of the Word, and the Spirits powerfull working with it. And without this new Birth there is no being ſaved, as our Saviour himſelfe affirmes, <hi>John</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p>§. 3. He is induſtrious after the meanes of Grace, loves to heare Chriſts voyce, and delights in it, as finding a ſweet reliſh therein; is able to know when he ſpeaketh, and when the tempter; he receives the Word not as the word of men, but as it is in deed the Word of God, with all readineſſe; for he reſiſts not as the wicked doe, but obeyes Chriſts call; which worketh in him mightily: for he findes it by experience quick, and powerfull, and ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then any two edged ſword; piercing even to the dividing aſunder of the ſoule and ſpirit, and of the joynts and marrow; and to the diſcerning of the very thoughts, and the moſt ſecret intents of the heart.</p>
               <p>§. 4. His heart is circumciſed, or rather God takes away the ſtony heart out of his fleſh, and gives him a new heart; in which he writes his Law, and puts a new ſpirit into him, even his owne Spirit; cauſing him to walke in his ſtatutes, and keep his ordinances ſo as to doe them.</p>
               <p>§. 5. He ſheds his love abroad in his heart by the Holy Ghoſt, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth to his conſcience, that he is become the childe of God; whereby he hath union, and communion with Chriſt; partakes of the Divine Nature, and becomes like God in holineſſe.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119873:3"/>
               <p>§. 6. He is brought out of darkneſſe into marvellous light, hath his eyes opened to ſee the wonders of Gods Law; and that vayle, or curtaine which before was drawne over his heart, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15, 16.) taken away, and is turned from the power of Satan unto God.</p>
               <p>§. 7. He is aſhamed of his former converſation, bewayles, and mournes bitterly for all his ſins, actuall and originall, of omiſſion, and commiſſion; ſecret, as well as knowne; leſſer, as well as greater: yea, as well for the evill which cleaves to his beſt workes, as for his evill workes; being more grieved for offending ſo good a God, then for that it doth, or might bring him ſhame, or puniſhment in this life, or in Hell.</p>
               <p>§. 8. He now findes that the Law is ſpirituall, binding the heart as well as the hands; to which holy and juſt rule he brings all his thoughts, words, and actions; and ſo ſees himſelfe out of meaſure ſinfull, as being guilty of all manner of concupiſcence; having broken every one of thoſe righteous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts (<hi>Exodus</hi> 20) more times and wayes then he hath haires on his head; not being able of himſelfe to thinke a good thought: for that all the powers of his ſoule, and members of his body, are wholly, and originally corrupted.</p>
               <p>§. 9. He ſees himſelfe as guilty of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, (being in his loynes) as any Heire is liable to his Fathers debt; and eſteemes it the Mother, and Nurſe of all: finding it like the great wheele in a Clocke, that ſets all the wheeles on moving, while it ſeemes to move ſloweſt; and therefore hates and bewailes it, as the moſt ſoule, hatefull, ſecret, deceitfull, and powerfull evill.</p>
               <p>§. 10. Whereupon finding himſelfe in a loſt condition, and confeſſing that he hath deſerved all the plagues of this life, and of that which is to come; and groaning under the burthen of ſinne, utterly diſpairing of all helpe in himſelfe; he is ſolicitouſly carefull in the uſe of the meanes, to attaine faith in the promiſe of Gods mercy made in Chriſt, finding no reſt untill he get ſome aſſurance, vehemently hungering and thirſting after, and earneſtly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the pardon of ſinne: waiting on the Lord with patience.</p>
               <p>§. 11. He humbly, unfainedly, and freely confeſſeth all his ſins ſo farre as he is able, with the ſeverall circumſtances which aggravate the ſame; to his owne ſhame, and Gods glory.</p>
               <p>§. 12. He will take an holy revenge on himſelfe, even to the denying of his owne reaſon and affections; his credit, carnall friends, profits, pleaſures, and whatever elſe might hinder: and by reſtoring goods, or monies evill gotten; though it were long ſince, and when he was a ſervant: in caſe he be able.</p>
               <p>§. 13. He unfainedly deſires to forſake all ſinne, as being in ſome meaſure dead to it, Chriſt (by his Spirit) having freed him from the power and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion thereof, and in part aboliſhed it; at leaſt he ſo parts from all iniquity, and hates every falſe way, that no one ſinne doth raigne in him; for when he doth commit any evill, it is full ſore againſt his will, as being led captive to it by the ſtrength of Satans temptations, and his owne corruptions; for he never
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119873:3"/>commits it freely and willingly, and with full conſent: he allowes not of the evill he does, no he will not premeditately, and in times not utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted; doe the leaſt evill, that the greateſt good may come of it: neither is there any ſinne he knowes by himſelfe, (were it formerly never ſo pleaſing to him) but he deſires as heartily, that he might never commit it; as that God ſhould never impute it. He likewiſe hates ſinne throughly and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, and therefore is truly grieved for the abominations that are done by others; to the diſhonour of God, and ſlander of religion, or the ruine of mens ſoules.</p>
               <p>§. 14. Nor does he only abhorre and depart from evill, but he cleaves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which is good; he is not only dead to, and made free from ſinne, but as he hath once been the ſervant of ſinne, ſo he becomes the ſervant of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; and as he hath been inſtrumentall to Satan, ſo he will now be as active to ſerve Chriſt; and be as fruitfull in good workes, as he hath formerly been in evill workes.</p>
               <p>§. 15. He is conformed to the image of Chriſt, and is led by the Spirit; walkes in newneſſe of life, lives holily, juſtly, and unblameably, for now he walkes not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit, and brings forth the fruits of the Spirit mentioned, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. ſo that he is changed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in every part, power, and faculty; his underſtanding is enlightened, his minde renewed, his will changed, his affections ſanctified, &amp;c. and he who thinkes he beleeves, and findes not a palpable change in his judgement, affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and actions, does but deceive himſelfe.</p>
               <p>§. 16. He goes often, and upon all occaſions to God in prayer, in which lyes all his ſtrength; yet not as his, but as it is the interceſſion of Gods owne Spirit in him, poured out in the name of Chriſt, and according to his Will; for being truly ſenſible of his ſins, and wants, he chiefly prayes for the pardon of ſinne, the effuſion of grace, and for the aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit; that he may more firmely beleeve, more ſoundly repent, more zealouſly doe, more patiently ſuffer, and more conſtantly perſevere in the practice and profeſſion of every duty. Nor does he for the moſt part fall into prayer without medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and preparation; nor utter words without devotion, and affection; nor without ſome aſſurance, and perſwaſion that God will heare, and grant his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts: yea, he moſtly takes notice of his enlargements in prayer, and of the ſucceſſe afterwards, and is accordingly thankfull, or humbled; not that he meaſureth Gods hearing his ſuit by his preſent anſwer, or his preſent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer by his owne ſence; he will pray (at leaſt in ſome poore meaſure) at all times, ſtriving againſt deadneſſe of ſpirit, and diſtractions, as an heavie burthen.</p>
               <p>§. 17. He heares the Word with attention, mindes, obſerves, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members it carefully; receives, and applyes whatſoever precept or promiſe is ſpoken out of the Word, as ſpoken by God to himſelfe in particular; is aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at the deepneſſe of Gods wiſedome, power, and goodneſſe; ſeriouſly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119873:4"/>meditating upon the Nature, Attributes, Word, and Workes of God: he layes it up in his heart, ponders on it in his mind, and practiſeth it in his life; neither will he approach unto the Lords Table, without due examination and preparation.</p>
               <p>§. 18. He loves, and longs after a powerfull and ſearching Miniſtry above all earthly treaſures, as finding a greater neceſſity of Spirituall then Corporall food; and therefore will take any paines, or be at any coſt, or ſuffer any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to injoy it.</p>
               <p>§. 19. He is never offended at any wholſome truth, be it never ſo untooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but affects that Miniſtery moſt which moſt layes open, and rebukes his owne ſinne; even therefore comming to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt. When he heares his owne ſins ſpoken againſt, he does not apply the ſame unto others, as is the mannor of too many; nor is he wiſe to defend the evill he does, but loves to be admoniſhed; nor will he after war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and conviction from the Word, goe on in an evill way, becauſe his principall care is to be ſaved.</p>
               <p>§. 20. He will not plead againſt God, nor aske a reaſon of his actions; if he meets with hard Scriptures he runs not into error, nor is offended, but ſuſpends his judgement, and blames his owne blindneſſe; you may know him from an unbeleever by this, he is wiſe to defend the truth when he heares it ſpoken againſt, but never argues againſt it; whereas the unbeleever (being prompt by Satan) can moſt ſubtilly argue againſt the truth, though he hath not a word to ſpeake for it; yea, he thinkes it religion enough if he can but diſpute againſt the religious, which is a manifeſt ſigne of a wicked man. Briefly, he neither carpes nor frets againſt a faithfull Miniſter, nor ſeekes to intrap him, or pervert what he delivers, but prayes for him, and is ready to ſpeake in his defence.</p>
               <p>§. 21. He hath an high eſtimation of the Miniſters, and meanes by which he was converted, and findes more ſweetneſſe in the Goſpell then in any thing elſe in the world.</p>
               <p>§. 22. Spirituall judgements, (as a famine of the Word, the blindneſſe of mens mindes, hardneſſe of their hearts, &amp;c.) he accounts more wofull then any judgement the world can be ſenſible of.</p>
               <p>§. 23. He is enlightened with the ſaving knowledge, and hid things of the Goſpell; and to ſee truth from error, good from evill; together with his owne wretchedneſſe by ſinne, and the riches of Gods free grace and mercy in Chriſt towards his owne ſoule; he is not ignorant of the principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as moſt aged people are; but is able and ready to give a reaſon of the hope that is in him.</p>
               <p>§. 24. He prayes for the enlargement, and rejoyces at the progreſſe of the Goſpell, and in the common good of the Church; and ſo at the graces or good ſucceſſe of any member in particular, and will be ſome way inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall for Chriſt, praying for, and earneſtly deſiring the ſalvation of others;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119873:4"/>and likewiſe endeavouring to win all he can to Chriſt; rejoycing no leſſe when any good thing is done by others, then if himſelfe did it. He highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects all ſuch as any way promote the Goſpell, and is thankfull to them.</p>
               <p>§. 25. He is willing to be at coſt to ſerve the Lord, will freely adminiſter carnall things, where he partaketh of ſpirituall things; and counts the ſame as a due, not as a benevolence: yea, he thinkes it moſt juſt, that they who preach the Goſpell ſhould live of the Goſpell; and that as freely as men of other Callings: which ſigne or character ſhewes, a world of men that profeſſe themſelves Chriſtians to be but counterfeits.</p>
               <p>§. 26. He beleeves impartially the whole Word of God, threats, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, as well as promiſes; and things above the reach of reaſon, as well as what experience hath made plaine to him; he feeles the power and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of Gods Word and Spirit, perſwading his conſcience, that his ſinnes are pardoned in Chriſt, and he in favour with God; ſo that he can truly apply Chriſt, and all his benefits and promiſes unto his owne ſoule; truſting in him, and caſting himſelfe only upon him for pardon and ſalvation.</p>
               <p>§. 27. He hath a ſweet and ſanctified peace in his conſcience, ariſing from the aſſured forgiveneſſe of his ſinnes, a ſound and ſtrong joy in the Lord, and in his Word through beleeving; not ſeldome the Holy Ghoſt inwardly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting too Gods privie ſeale, by ſudden refreſhings falling like the dew upon his heart, and eſtabliſhing his ſoule before the Lord, eſpecially after holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; yea, his hope (as being built upon Gods Word, and promiſes) fills him with ſuch joy unſpeakeable, that it makes him rejoyce even in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation.</p>
               <p>§. 28. He ſometimes loſeth the efficacie, feeling, and comfort of faith, but the ſeed and habit of faith alwaies remaineth. He is often and grievouſly aſſaulted with feares, and doubtings, but in the iſſue he alwaies gets the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and is the more aſſured, for having been ſo much aſſaulted, and does ſo much the more ſtrive to make his Calling and Election ſure; and to be aſſured of future happineſſe after this his earthly pilgrimage.</p>
               <p>§. 29. Or, if he hath but a weake faith yet it is ſound, againſt which the very gates of Hell ſhall never prevaile, for he never utterly falls away from the grace of God, but perſeveres in the truth, and in well doing to the end; and therein findes alſo a bleſſed thriving, and gracious progreſſe in true holineſſe.</p>
               <p>§. 30. He is perfectly juſtified by the bloud of Chriſt, freed from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the Law, and in ſome good meaſure from the ſpirit of bondage; is often in combate between the fleſh and the Spirit, but the Spirit in the end ever gets the upper hand.</p>
               <p>§. 31. And as he beleeves in his heart, ſo he is not aſhamed of the Croſſe of Chriſt, but will profeſſe the truth boldly in all eſtates, and in times of ſuffering, and publiſh what Chriſt hath done for his ſoule to Gods glory, and the comfort of others; yea, if called to it, he will, God aſſiſting him, lay
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119873:5"/>downe his life for Chriſt, and the Goſpell; and rejoyce alſo, that he is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy.</p>
               <p>§. 32. Neither is he high-minded, but more feares the want of grace then confides in what he hath, for he workes out his ſalvation with feare and trembling; and truſts not in the leaſt to his owne ſtrength, but is ever jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and ſuſpicious, leaſt his heart ſhould deceive him; but he reſolves by <hi>Gods</hi> grace not to uſe any unlawfull meanes, nor yeeld to any thing againſt the truth, for the avoyding of what he feares, be it burning at a ſtake; as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and being fully perſwaded, that all things ſhall worke together for the beſt unto him. And indeed the feare of <hi>God,</hi> (which is his continuall guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dion) keepes him in ſome meaſure from the feare of death, and terrour of the world; for he feares not them that can onely kill the body, in any degree like him, that after he hath killed can caſt both body and ſoule into Hell. Nor does he grutch to loſe a temporall life, when in lieu thereof he ſhall obtaine an eternall Crowne of glory.</p>
               <p>§. 33. He is wonderfully inflamed with the love and eſtimation of <hi>God,</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> eſpecially upon the returne of his prayers, or the obtaining of ſome mercy; the which he ſhewes by his hating of evill, and by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant obedience, and the delight he hath in keeping of <hi>Gods</hi> Commandements, and by his willingneſſe to be at coſt, or ſuffer for him. Neither is he ſo in love with the world, or any thing in it, as that it ſhall diminiſh his love to <hi>God;</hi> yea he ſo loves and longs for <hi>Chriſts</hi> appearing, that he may be united to him, and enjoy his preſence; that his daily prayer is, Come Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> come quickly.</p>
               <p>§. 34. Againe, he intirely loves, and highly eſteemes <hi>Gods</hi> people, not out of any carnall or ſelfe ends, but for their graces, the truths ſake; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are borne of <hi>God:</hi> more loving and honouring the poore that walke uprightly, then they that pervert their wayes though they be rich; and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them beſt that ſerve <hi>God</hi> moſt: He is prone to juſtifie them, and ſpeake in their defence when he heares them reviled, ſlandered, or contemned by wicked and ungodly men, though he incur their diſpleaſure by it.</p>
               <p>§. 35. He does not eſtrange himſelfe from the people of <hi>God</hi> in their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, but is ready to miniſter unto them when they ſtand in need, and uſe any meanes for their reliefe. He will ſolicite great ones in their behalfe, and in <hi>Chriſts</hi> cauſe, though he indanger himſelfe thereby; and can be as ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt a Suitor at the Throne of Grace for others that are in diſtreſſe, as for himſelfe, even thurſting, and ſtudying how he may doe them moſt good, as participating, and being touched with compaſſion, and having a fellow-feeling both of the miſery and felicity of others, as one member hath of another; eſpecially of the Churches, as a member hath of the whole body. Neither can he rejoyce in his owne peace and welfare, while the Church and people of <hi>God</hi> are in diſtreſſe, whoſe welfare he preferres before his owne.</p>
               <p>§. 36. He delights in the Saints company above all others, as finding an
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119873:5"/>heavenly ſweetneſſe in their conference and ſociety, where every ones words doe ſavour of grace and wiſedome; and when in every company he ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe good, or receive good.</p>
               <p>§. 37. And as he loves and delights in holy company, ſo he loathes evill company; neither will he have any fellowſhip with the workers of iniquity, or be in league with the wicked; as Swearers, Drunkards, Whooremongers, Scoffers, &amp;c. but avoyd all needleſſe ſociety with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="insert">
               <div type="notice">
                  <pb n="A" facs="tcp:119873:7"/>
                  <p>[<hi>Place theſe</hi> 25. <hi>Sections next after page</hi> 10. §. 37.]</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Such other ſignes or properties of <hi>A true Beleever,</hi> as offered themſelves while the ſecond ſheet was (by a provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) ſomewhat long in printing.</head>
                  <p>1. §.</p>
                  <p>HE will neither back-bite others, nor give eare to back-biters of others. Neither lend Satan his tougue to utter, nor his eares to heare, nor his heart to beleeve lyes and ſlanders. He will not leſſen his owne credit, by traducing one that wrongs him: he will not leſſen his owne ſhame, and blame, by traducing one he hath wronged: as too many doe. He wonders not ſo much at anothers ingratitude to him: as at his owne unthankfulneſſe to <hi>God.</hi> He will pardon many things in others, which he will not tolerate in himſelfe. He will neither arrogate to himſelfe, nor derogate from another: neither villifie other mens doings nor over highly prize his owne. He will not condemne, cenſure, or ſlight that which he underſtands not. To finde gall in a Pidgion, a knot in a Bulruſh where is none: is none of his humour. In relating an enemies words, he will neither adde to them; nor diminiſh from them. The faults of a few, ſhall not make him uncharitable to all: nor the goodneſſe of many, make him credulous of the reſt. He envies none for doing, or faring, or being better eſteemed then himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. §. His graces, and goodneſſe gaines him more enemies; and breeds him more danger, then vice and wickedneſſe does another man: but he is more pleaſed then diſpleaſed at it, for he knowes by the worlds hating of him, that he is not of the world; but that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath choſen him out of the world: and that he ſome way diſcovers the worlds treaſons, and deceits. He knowes alſo that to be the worlds friend, is to be <hi>Gods</hi> enemy; yea he eſteemes it an honour to be evill ſpoken of, by evill men: (becauſe when a thing is beſt, they will like it leaſt:) and a grace, to be diſgraced for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was farre more diſgraced for him. Beſides, the ſingle approbation of one wiſe experimentall <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> is enough with him, to countervaile the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, and diſlike of a whole Pariſh of ſenſualiſts; and an ounce of credit with <hi>God,</hi> more worth then a tallent of mens praiſes. And how little is that man hurt, whom malice condemnes on earth, and <hi>God</hi> commends in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? If he cannot avoyd their malice, and evill words; he will be ſure not to deſerve them; which is much at one upon the matter: for as the beſt confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their ſlanders, is (not by our great words, but) by our good works:
<pb n="B" facs="tcp:119873:8"/>ſo his conſcience knowing him innocent, like a conſtant friend takes him by the hand, and cheeres him againſt all his miſeries. However, he will not in the leaſt wrong his conſcience; to avoyd the imputation of ſingularity. The ſcoffes of <hi>Atheiſts</hi> ſhall not beat him off from his Profeſſion: No, if he does well, hath <hi>Gods</hi> Word for his warrant, and glory for his aime, nothing can daunt or diſcourage him. Neither the threatnings of fire, nor the faire, and large promiſes of cunning, and cruell adverſaries; neither paine, nor loſſe can make him ſhrinke from <hi>Chriſt;</hi> much leſſe the cenſures, and ſcoffes of lewd perſons. The conſcience of good intentions, let their ſucceſſe be what it will: is both a ſufficient diſcharge, and comfort to his generous minde.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. §. Through the ſtuddy of vertue, and Chriſtian prudence; he makes the ſervile paſſions of his minde, (feare and anger) ſubject to the more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faculties of his ſoule, reaſon and underſtanding. As appeares in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of an enemy; for let him be injured, he will both forbeare, and forgive: well conſidering, that <hi>it is the glory of a man to paſſe by an offence:</hi> and that it is greater fortitude, to overcome his owne paſſions, then to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh a City. Wherefore in ſtead of returning like for like; he will pacifie his enemy with milde words, and gentle behaviour: which may be reſembled to Milke that quencheth Wild-fire; or Oyle that quenches Lime, which by water is kindled: and thinkes it enough for one to be angry at a time. He is not like our Ruffians, and <hi>ſonnes of Beliall:</hi> who when they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with others, will fly in their Makers face, and teare the name of their Saviour in peeces: even ſwearing away their part in that Blood, which muſt ſave them if ever they be ſaved. Nor like our Gallants, whom the Devill hath ſo blinded and bewitched: that they will contend for the way, and ſtrive for the wall even to the death: and kill one another, as though either of their honours, were of more worth; then both their ſoules. Or admit one get the victory, miſerable is that victory wherein thou overcomeſt thine enemy and thy paſſions, yea the Devill in the meane time overcomes thee: perhaps thou ſlayeſt his body, but the Devill ſlayes thy ſoule. Nor like thoſe ſooles you ſee walking in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall;</hi> that like two Cockes of the Game, peck out one anothers eyes to make the <hi>Lawyers</hi> ſport. No ſayes he, why ſhould I vexe my ſelfe, becauſe another hath vexed me? Or why ſhould I doe my ſelfe a ſhrewd turne, becauſe another would? And admit carnall reaſon ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge to him, that his enemy is unworthy to be forgiven: rectified reaſon will anſwer, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> is worthy to be obeyed, who hath commanded me to forgive him. And well may I beare with him, when his Maker beares with me: and forgive him, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath forgiven me much more. Nor can any repute him a coward for this his humble patience: the true coward is your Hot-ſpur; that feares the blaſts of mens breath, and not the fire of <hi>Gods</hi> wrath: that trembles at the thought of a Priſon, and yet feares not Hell fire. But the Beleever is as <hi>bold as a Lion</hi> if his cauſe be good; yea to ſpeake
<pb n="C" facs="tcp:119873:8"/>rightly, there is no ſuch coward, none ſo valliant as the Beleever: without <hi>Gods</hi> warrant he dares doe nothing, with it any thing. He feares none but the diſpleaſure of the higheſt, and runs away from nothing but ſinne. Indeed he more feares the leaſt ſinne, then the greateſt torment: as may be ſeene in the <hi>Martyrs</hi> that noble Army. But he is ſo farre from fearing an impotent enemy, that he feares not death it ſelfe: no not the <hi>Day of Judgement,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.17. Luke 21.25. to 29. yea he is ſo ſtrong withall, that he is able to prevaile with <hi>God,</hi> Gen. 32.26.28. Exod. 32.10. And overcome the <hi>world,</hi> the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devill,</hi> 1 John 2.14. and 5.4. Gal. 5.24. and all this by his faith and prayer; and not ſeldome does he overcome his <hi>enemy</hi> too, by well-doing: for he lives ſo well, that his back-biting adverſaries are either put to ſilence, or conſtrained to praiſe <hi>God,</hi> and ſpeake well of him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. §. He is more knowing then the men of the world: for as he hath the light of the Spirit, and the eye of ſaith above them: ſo the Word of <hi>Chriſt</hi> dwelleth in him plentifully, in all wiſedome, and ſpirituall underſtanding: and he increaſeth daily in the knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> and of our Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> becauſe <hi>God</hi> reveales himſelfe to him, in a great meaſure as to his friend. Beſides, his knowledge is about the beſt things; and one drop of ſoule wiſedome, and ſaving knowledge; guided by the feare of <hi>God:</hi> is more worth then all humane learning. And to this knowledge, unbeleevers are meere ſtrangers. Yea be they never ſo wiſe, and learned in other things; they have onely the theory of this wiſedome; they can prattle of it by roate, but they know not what it is by effect, and experience. Yea if a man want faith, holineſſe, the love of <hi>God,</hi> and the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> to be his teacher: he ſhall not be able really, and by his owne experience, to know the chiefe points of Chriſtian Religion; ſuch as are <hi>faith, repentance, regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> the <hi>love of God,</hi> the <hi>preſence of the Spirit,</hi> the <hi>remiſſion of ſinnes,</hi> the <hi>effuſion of grace,</hi> the <hi>poſſeſſion of heavenly comforts:</hi> not what the <hi>peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and <hi>joy in the Holy Ghoſt</hi> is; nor what the <hi>communion of Saints</hi> meanes; when every one of theſe are eaſie, and familiar to the meaneſt, and ſimpleſt Beleever. And the reaſon is, the Beleever digeſts his knowledge into pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and imployes it to the glory of the Giver, his neighbours good, and the furthering of his owne ſalvation. He is neither ungrounded in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion, nor unconcionable in the practice. Each Booke or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, both increaſeth his knowledge, and leſſens his vices. Yea he will pick ſomething out of every thing; and gather honey from the ſelfe ſame thing, that others will poyſon. Anothers hating the truth, ſhall make him love it the more; for he is inſtructed both by ſimilitude, and contrariety. Whereas let the unbeleever know never ſo much; he is reſolved to be never the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and they who are unwilling to obey, <hi>God</hi> thinkes unworthy to know. Whence it is alſo, that as what the Beleever doth is good for the matter, ſo he will doe it well alſo for the manner: and in all his actions obſerve, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his ends be good, or evill: for he will doe good actions, with good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions;
<pb n="D" facs="tcp:119873:9"/>and not be moved unto them, by baſe ends as is the unbeleever. Nor is he puſſed up either with his knowledge, or parts: well knowing that he is ignorant of many things, for a few that he underſtands: and that he falls ſhort of others, in what he moſt excells. Nor will he build upon his knowledge; but in caſes doubtfull; he will adviſe with others. Yea he will ſubmit to the better advice, even of his inferiour, or Maid-ſervant.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. §. He is not erronious in his judgement; he neither affects curioſity, nor ſingularity: which is the fooliſh ambition of unbleſt underſtandings. But he wholly applyes himſelfe to thoſe things, which <hi>God</hi> hath revealed in his Word; and to the confirmation of received truths; which is the meekneſſe, and humility of the beſt judgements: and ſo is wiſe according to ſobriety. Nor does he ſo cry up Juſtification, as to cry downe, and quite overthrow Sanctification. He reades, and heares with an honeſt, and good heart: and to the end onely that he may know ſavingly, beleeve rightly, and live religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly: and <hi>God</hi> grants his deſire in all the three. He is reſolved to doe <hi>Gods</hi> Will, therefore <hi>God</hi> gives him to know the Doctrine; whether it be of <hi>God</hi> or no. Neither will he give heed nor lend his eare to the intiſing words of falſe Prophets, or ſpirits of error: who ſpeake lyes through hypocriſie; as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their conſciences burned with an hot iron. None can beguile him with their ſleights, and cunning craftineſſe whereby they lye in wait to deceive: for his heart is ſtabliſhed with grace. He is not wavering, nor carried about with every winde of Doctrine, which vaine talkers, and deceivers of mindes daily vent: becauſe he is rooted, and ſtabliſhed in the faith. He avoides all prophane, and vaine bablings; all fooliſh, and unlearned queſtions which are endleſſe, all ſtrife about words, which is to no profit: all Jewiſh fables, and commandments of men, and geneologies: which breed vaine jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, rather then godly edification which is by faith, all brawlings, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about the Law; as being unprofitable, and vaine. He will not be ſpoyled through Philoſophy, or great ſhewes of learning. He doteth not about fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſputations, and things that ingender unto more ungodlineſſe: as knowing well, that the words of theſe falſe Apoſtles, and Teachers of lyes fret like a Canker, poyſon mens judgements, and pervert their ſimple and ſuperſtitious hearers: but rather ſtuddies to have a good conſcience, and faith unfained. Whereas it is the portion of all rotten hearted, and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall Profeſſors: to be given up to errour, and to beleeve lyes. In briefe, he will entertaine nothing which is contrary to wholſome Doctrine; and not according to the glorious <hi>Goſpell,</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>God.</hi> Yea if there be any that erre concerning the truth, or having a ſhew of godlineſſe deny the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of it: he turnes away from ſuch. Againe, he is not for <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Apollos,</hi> nor <hi>Cephas;</hi> but for all, that bring the Word for their warrant. And thoſe who will not ſuffer wholſome Doctrine, but having their eares itching, doe after their owne luſts get them an heap of Teachers: turning their eares from the truth, being given unto fables: are farre from being of his minde. He is
<pb n="E" facs="tcp:119873:9"/>none of thoſe that creep into Houſes, and lead captive ſimple women laden with ſins; and led away with divers luſts: that ſubvert whole families, by walking in craftineſſe; and handling the Word deceitfully; and that teach things which they ought not, for filthy lucres ſake: even delighting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their deceivings: that beguile unſtable ſoules by promiſing them liberty, and are themſelves the ſervants of corruption, being men of corrupt mindes, that reſiſt the truth; and are reprobate concerning the faith. He will reject him that is an Heriticke, after once, or twice admonition: know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he who is ſuch, is perverted, and ſinneth deing damned of his owne ſelfe. He is no cauſer of diviſion, or diſſention in the Church.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. §. But he wins many to the truth, for he is charitable, wiſhes all good, and happy like himſelfe: and accordingly proves a meanes of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and that two wayes. Firſt whereas others by their evill example, are a meanes to deſtroy many: he by his good example, is a meanes to ſave many. For he is upright, and ſincere hearted to <hi>God</hi> and man. He is none of thoſe that profeſſe <hi>God</hi> with their words, and with their workes deny him. He is not double-tongued, but as he thinkes in his heart, ſo he ſpeakes with his mouth: and as he is led by his conſcience, ſo his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is led by truth. In fine, he is knowne from another man, onely by the holineſſe, and uprightneſſe of his life, and converſation. Yea all may read in his life, that he beleeves in his heart: and are forced to ſay, This is a good <hi>God,</hi> whoſe ſervant is ſo good. Or this is a good, holy, and opperative Religion: that thus changes, and transformes men into new Creatures. For his life is like a precious and ſweet perſume: whoſe ſavour ſpreads it ſelfe, and is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to all that come neare. Yea, be ſowes thoſe good workes, that remaine to poſterity, and are reaped by ſucceſſion: and he ſhall be happy in making others ſo. But ſecondly, as the wicked draw all they can to Hell by their alurements; and ſubtill perſwaſions: ſo he drawes all he can to <hi>Heaven,</hi> by his admonitions, and ſweet compellations. He loves the ſoule of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and therefore he will tell him of his faults, and the Judgements of <hi>God</hi> due unto the ſame. Yea rather then let one goe headlong to deſtruction, he will violently plucke him out of the fire; for he hath not onely zeale, but courage to doe good: he is not luke warme, nor will he ſuffer diſcretion to eat up his devotion; as it fares with common profeſſors. For he had rather hazzard the cenſure of ſome, then hinder the good of others. Yea rather then be guilty of other mens ſins. By his cowardly ſilence, he can afford to be deſpiſed, and thought out of his wits by the world; reputed a foole, and pointed at in the ſtreets. For he preferres <hi>Gods</hi> favour, before all the worlds: and his glory, before his owne credit. Not that he wants wit, or deſerves contempt: for his zeale is mixed with diſcretion, and he makes knowledge the pilot of his devotion: but his love to <hi>God</hi> is ſuch, as he cannot beare with them that are evill. His righteous ſoule is vexed with ſeeing, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the uncleanly converſation of their unlawfull deeds. Yea it cuts his very
<pb n="F" facs="tcp:119873:10"/>heart to heare, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo wounded with oathes, blaſphemies, and reproaches, who is the life of his life, and ſoule of his ſoule. And his love to ſinners alſo, for his zeale againſt them, is a ſweet compound of love, and anger: for though he hates the vices of a wicked man, yet he loves his perſon: he can chide him ſharply, and yet at the ſame time pray for him heartily. Whereby he not ſeldome ſaves his brother, for he findes favour in the ſight of God, and prevailes with him for things hard to be obtained. As when <hi>Stevens</hi> prayer prevailed for perſecuting <hi>Paul;</hi> and our <hi>Saviours</hi> prayer for his murtherers.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. §. He is not ſordedly covetous, nor given to filthy lucre: for the covetous perſon is an Idolator, and hath no inheritance in the Kingdome of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of <hi>God.</hi> And therefore cannot poſſibly be a <hi>Beleever;</hi> nor doe we read of one godly perſon in the whole <hi>Bible,</hi> that was covetous. He is contented with things neceſſary, and deſires not great matters: for if he have food, and raiment, he will therewith be content: conſidering how they that will needs be rich, fall into temptations, and ſnares, and into many fooliſh, and noyſome luſts; which drowne men in perdition, and deſtruction. And that the deſire of mony, is the root of all evill: which while ſome luſted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; they erred from the faith, and peirced themſelves through with many ſorrowes. He will neither defraud, nor oppreſſe his brother in any matter: he will not deale unjuſtly in line, in weight, or in meaſure. He luſteth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forbidden fruit; nor coveteth that which is anothers. He will not remove his neighbours Land marke, nor conceale any Deeds, or Writings, that make for his neighbours advantage. If his neighbour ſuffer prejudice, or loffe in any thing belonging to him; through his, or his ſervants meanes: he will make him recompence to the full. In caſe his Cattell breake into his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours ground, and eat his Corne, or Graſſe: he will willingly, and without compulſion ſatisfie for the damage. He will not detaine the poore Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hire, untill the morning: leaſt his family ſhould want Bread for the preſent. He loves Juſtice in the leaſt things, and deſires rather to buy what he would have; then that it be given him. Chuſing to eat his owne bread, and to drinke water out of his owne Ceſterne. He hateth gifts, leaſt they ſhould corrupt his judgement; and make him partiall. Nor is he legally juſt, or conſcionable according to the ſtatute only; but piouſly juſt. If his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tells him, that he hath any way prejudiced his neighbour, though there be noue to witneſſe againſt him; though it be unknowne to the party himſelfe that ſuffers the damage: he will make him ſatisfaction, and never thinke he merits by it. If he finde any thing, he both deſires, and indeavours to finde out the owner; that he may reſtote it. He will not take advantege from his neighbours poverty, or ſimplicity to oppreſſe, or couſen him. He will not compound with Creditors, for ten ſhillings in the pound: when he is able to pay all. He will not take an enemies goods, or the goods of an Heathen: though it be beyond the Line; without making ſatisfaction, or
<pb n="G" facs="tcp:119873:10"/>returning a valuable conſideration: although the Lawes of the Land wil beare him out in it: yea although he have Letters of Markq, for his warrant unleſſe there be ſome other cauſe. If he make an oath, or promiſe, though to his, and <hi>Gods</hi> enemy; and to his great diſadvantage: he will faithfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, and not violate the ſame. Before he uſeth the extremity, either of Law, or of Armes; he offers conditions of peace: and before he will fall to blowes, he will try what reaſon will doe; ſoundly examine the cauſe, and heare what the party can ſay for himſelfe: and after that, he will rather ſuffer, and yeeld ſome part of his right; then doe wrong, contend, or goe to Law. For he will not doe all he may, leaſt evill men ſpeake ill of him, or inſult; as they are very prone to doe; by reaſon of their ſpight at Religion. Laſtly, he ſeldome but gets the victory; yea it is rare if he be vanquiſht, either in going to Law, or making War: becauſe he never undertakes War, or Suit, without juſt cauſe; and to a good intent. Yea it is rare alſo, if this be not the iſſue: the leſſe he covets, the more he hath: and the leſſe he thirſts after theſe temporall things; the more he covets ſpirituall things.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. §. Neither love, nor hatred ſhall rob him of his judgement; or make him partiall. He will neither eſteeme Father, nor Mother, nor Wife, nor Childe: ſo as to diſobey <hi>God</hi> in the leaſt for their ſakes, He will not wrong his Children by a former Wife; to give that which is due unto them, unto the Children of a ſecond Wife: but he will make his firſt borne Heire, and give him a double portion of all that he hath. If his Sonne be ſtubborne, and diſobedient; a Riater, and a Drunkard: he will not nouriſh him in it; but inflict due puniſhment upon him, according to his demerits. He will not ſeek to ſave a Murtherer from death: leaſt he make the whole Land guilty of blood. No, be it his owne Sonne, leaſt in ſaving him from a temporall ſhame, and puniſhment; he ſhould bring upon him an eternall: and in liew of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his body, he ſhould deſtroy his ſoule. Beſides, he will rather his owne Childe ſhall be deſtroyed, then <hi>God</hi> diſhonoured, and his Law not executed. It matters not to him what others would doe, nor what all the world ſayes, if they bring not a written word; they prevaile nothing: he will goe on in his uprightneſſe, and not ſhame to be ſingular: as more fearing <hi>Gods</hi> anger, then the worlds ſcornes. Neither cuſtome, nor example of his fore-fathers will he follow; without, or againſt the written Word. No, he will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Panl</hi> himſelfe, any further then he followes <hi>Chriſt.</hi> He remembers how vaine, ignorant, and ſinfull his former converſation (which he received by the traditions of his Fathers) was: and thinkes it too much to continue ſtill therein. Nor will he take incouragement from the <hi>Saints</hi> falls; to doe the like: but they ſhall ſerve him as Sea-markes, to make him beware. Indeed when things are of a doubtfull nature; he will take the ſureſt (not the ſtrongeſt) fide; and which draws neareſt to probability: and where the Law written doth ceaſe; he will obſerve that which is allowed by the practiſe and cuſtom of the godly, and religious.</p>
                  <pb n="H" facs="tcp:119873:11"/>
                  <p n="9">9. §. He honours, and obeyes his Parents: and <hi>God</hi> accordingly proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him; and prolongeth his dayes. If they ſtand in need, he will nouriſh, and maintaine them: as they did him, in his need. If a ſervant, he ſerves his Maſter with ſingleneſſe of heart, as unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not with eye-ſervice, but out of conſcience. And the Lord is with him, and proſpereth all he takes in hand; gives him ſuch favour in his Maſters ſight; that he truſteth him with all he hath. Yea the Lord bleſſeth his Maſter, and all the family fares the better for his ſake. He will not be charitable with his Maſters goods, nor waſtfull with his Parents. If a Maſter he uſeth his ſervants ſo, as conſidering that himſelfe is a ſervant, to a greater Maſter. To a good ſervant, he is kinde, and liberall: and having ſtaid long with him, and done him good, and faithfull ſervice: he will at the end of his yeares, not onely make him free; but give him a bountifull reward, anſwerable to the good ſervice he hath performed: and by this he is more inriched. He will not bid his ſervants tell lyes, or being at home, to ſay that he is abroad. He loves not to raile, or ſpeake evill of <hi>Magiſtrates.</hi> as being ſent of <hi>God,</hi> for the puniſhment of evill doers; and for the praiſe of them that doe well. In chouſing them, he will have reſpect to their piety, and fitneſſe: and not to wealth, favour, or any other either private or baſe ends. He is no Neuter, when <hi>Gods</hi> cauſe is in danger: but he will helpe the Lord againſt the mighty. He imployes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in ſome lawfull calling; he lives not idely. He will not company with wicked perſons; for feare of being infected by them: nor joyne in Marriage either with Idolaters, or prophane perſons: leaſt he ſhould learn their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes. Nor give his Children in marriage to them, for the ſame reaſon. He is carefull to preſerve his Childrens chaſtity: and therefore he will in due time, provide fit matches for them. Be he Parent, Maſter, or Magiſtrate; he will thinke it no diſparagement to his greatneſſe; if <hi>Chriſts</hi> Ambaſſadour ſhall as he is bound; require him to give ſome teſtimony that he is a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> before he intrudes himſelfe to the Lords Table. Yea, he will as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath commanded him; be ready to give a reaſon of the hope that is in him, though in the preſence of others that are not ſo rich, ancient, or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as himſelfe, though he was never in ſo many yeares examined: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed none but proud, and ignorant perſons; will ſtand upon compariſons in <hi>Gods</hi> Worſhip; for pretend they what they will, the genuine reaſon is; they are aſhamed to make knowne their ianorance. If a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> he will not preach to pleaſe, but to profit: nor will he date to ſerve at the Altar, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being holy.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. §. He hath low, and meane thoughts of himſelfe; therefore the Lord makes him excell, and ſhewes his ſtrength by him. He abhorres to thinke himſelfe better then others, becauſe <hi>God</hi> bleſſeth him more with outward bleſſings, or hath beſtowed more inward gifts and graces upon him, then upon others: well knowing that <hi>God</hi> reſiſteth the proud, and giveth grace to the humble. He is not lifted up, nor caſt downe with mens flatteries or
<pb n="I" facs="tcp:119873:11"/>ſlanpers. He forgets his good deeds, and therefore <hi>God</hi> remembers them: he remembers his evill deeds, therefore <hi>God</hi> forgets them. He is not envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, nor given to ſtrife; but of a meeke, and quiet ſpirit; peaceable, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and eaſie to be intreated. He affects rather plaineſſe then pompe: and will rather refuſe places of honour, then eagerly purſue after them. He never ſtands ſo ſecure, but he will take heed leaſt he fall: and preferres an humble feare, before a preſumptuous confidence. He makes conſcience of ſmall ſins, leaſt they ſhould prove wedges to greater. When he is tempted to evill, the feare of <hi>God</hi> keepes him innocent. And it is alwaies in his minde, that <hi>God</hi> ſeeth all things, and is ever beholding him. He will neither deny, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh, nor juſtitie his ſinne; nor ſhift it off to others. If he have falne into an evill, he will beware of doing it the ſecond time: well knowing that there is no laying hold of the Promiſes, without making conſcience, and obeying the Precepts. He will not mock his admoniſher, ſcoffe at the meanes to be ſaved; nor make himſelfe merry with his owne Damnation as the deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wicked doe. He turnes not his back upon any truth, nor flyes from any inſtruction; he hateth not the light: yea he loves that Miniſter beſt, that moſt makes manifeſt the ſecrets of his heart; as knowing that <hi>God</hi> is in him of a truth. He will not refuſe a Pardon, becauſe he diſlikes the Meſſenger. Indeed he leaſt regards thoſe <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that the world admires: as well weighing what St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. They are of the world, therefore ſpeake they of the world, and the world heareth them: we are of <hi>God,</hi> he that knoweth <hi>God</hi> heareth us; he that is not of <hi>God</hi> heareth not us: hereby know we the Spirit of truth, and the ſpirit of errour, ver. 5.6. He is faithfull to his friend; for his love extends to his ſoule: he will ſpeake of his faults to his face, of his vertues behinde his back. The deep, and devilliſh plots of wicked Polliticians; never enter into his thoughts: becauſe the feare of <hi>God</hi> keeps them out. Or if they offer to intrude themſelves; they have not the leaſt admittance: for he (ſo ſarre forth as he can) refraines all diſpute with ſinne, Satan, or his inſtruments. He is no Health-drinker; for he abhors Drunkenneſſe, as the root of all evill, and rot of all good: and ſcornes the reputation of good fellowſhip. He is none of thoſe that <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes of; who have eyes full of Adultery, and that cannot ceaſe to ſinne: that gaze upon every faire face, and luſt after every beautifull woman. He will not be caught, nor yeeld to the imbraces of an Harlot; though her lips drop like an Hony-combe, and her mouth be ſmoother then Oyle; though ſhe offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her ſelfe in the ſtreets, and lyeth in wait for him at every corner. Yea he is wiſe enough to conſider, that it may not be a woman, but the Devill in the likeneſſe of a woman as ſome have thus been cheated.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. §. So you have (in part) ſeene; how he loves, and ſeares, and ſerves the Lord; and ſeekes his glory, and the good of others: but (which is very obſerveable) ſhall I ſhew you how the Lord bleſſeth him, in every thing he takes in hand, or that does befall him? I pray obſerve the ſeveralls, and then
<pb n="K" facs="tcp:119873:12"/>if you be not yet a Beleever, you will neglect no meanes, indeavour, or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to obtaine ſuch a bleſſed condition; the particulars are many, ile mention a few only. Firſt if he be in proſperity, as he ſhall be ſure to have plenty of all outward things; if <hi>God</hi> ſees it would be good for him: ſo that he ſhall lend to others, but ſhall not borrow himſelfe. He will be accordingly thankfull, and as <hi>God</hi> bleſſeth him more or leſſe, ſo will he doe good; and the more rich, the more rich will he be in good workes, and the more ready to diſtribute, and communicate. For he is pittifull, and ready to ſhew mercy where is need; and to defend, reſcue, and deliver the oppreſſed, out of the hands of their enemies, and oppreſſors; if he have power, and opportunity to doe it. And by reaſon of his bountifulneſſe to the poore, he becommeth more rich; ſo that he is not more ready to pray, for bleſſings in his want: then he is to give thankes for them, being obtained. And be he never ſo rich; he is not high minded: neither does he truſt in uncertaine riches, but in the living <hi>God.</hi> For in his proſperity he forgetteth not his former low eſtate; but is ever meditating upon, and admiring the Lords goodneſſe towards him. Yea he ſets a <hi>Memorandum</hi> upon every remarkable mercy, that he may not forget it: and admires that <hi>God</hi> ſhould ſet his delight, and love upon him; and choſe him above many others; and this makes him ſtrive to ſurpaſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in his love, and ſervice to <hi>God</hi> againe. Whereas unbeleevers, when they are waxed fat with the good bleſſings of <hi>God;</hi> they will ſpurne with the heel, and forſake <hi>God</hi> that made them: not once regarding the ſtrong <hi>God</hi> of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; but provoke him with ſtrange <hi>gods,</hi> and other abominations: but it fares not ſo with the Beleever; neither doth he ſo requite the Lord. And as he is thankfull to the Author, ſo likewiſe to any that he ſhall make inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall for his good: thinking himſelfe bound to remember, and requite good turnes.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. §. Secondly, if he falls into adverſity, or any kinde of diſtreſſe; he knowes it is ſent of the Lord in love, and to doe him good, and to give him occaſion of rejoycing afterwards. He well conſiders, that ſcarfe any thing more proves us his, then his ſtripes: that ſtripes from the Almighty, are ſo farre from arguing his diſpleaſure, that contrarily there are few better tokens, and pledges of his adoption and love: and that they are baſtards, and not ſonnes who are without correction. And ſo it is, that as many as <hi>God</hi> loves, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes and chaſtens. And as it is ſent for his good, ſo it doth him good: croſſes in his eſtate, diſeaſes in his body, maladies in his minde, are medicines to his ſoule: the impairing of the one, is the repairing of the other. His ſinne dyes with his fame, or with his health, or with his peace, or with his outward eſtate. Yea it both leſſons his ſins, and increaſeth his graces: for <hi>God</hi> ſends him affliction both for his inſtruction, and reformation, to ſcoure away the ruſt of corruption, and to try the truth of his ſanctification; for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of his patience, and the exerciſe of his faith, and the improvement of his zeale, and to provoke his importunity, and to double his obligation; to
<pb n="L" facs="tcp:119873:12"/>greaten each other grace, and to augment his glory. Againe he inflicts a leſſe puniſhment, to avoyd a greater: and by ſmarting in his body, ſtate, or name; he is ſaved from ſmarting in his ſoule. He is chaſtned that he may be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; not confounded: his worſer part to wit his Body, ſtate, or name is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſht; that his better part, that is his ſoule, may be ſaved in the day of Judgement. But ſee it in ſome particulars, as firſt how it makes him humble, and thankfull: for he not only calls to minde his owne unworthineſſe of the leaſt mercy he ſtill injoyes; and how he hath provoked the Giver: (for he is ever meditating, of what <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath done, and ſuffered for him: and how he hath provoked <hi>Chriſt.</hi>) But he alſo compares what he ſuffers, with what he might have ſuffered; arguing thus with himſelfe, he that hath taken this from me, might have taken more: he that afflicts me for a time, could have held me longer; he that hath touched me in part, could have ſtricken me in whole: he that laid this upon my body, hath power to lay a greater Rod both upon my body and ſoule, without doing me the leaſt wrong. And ſo goes on, I was borne a childe of wrath, and whereas <hi>God</hi> might have left me in that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing condition and choſen others; he hath of his free grace adopted me, and left others. And this makes him cry out, O the depth! as a mercy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all expreſſion: ſaying further, O my ſoule, thou haſt not roome enough for thankfulneſſe! And the truth is, if we could but ſeriouſly thinke upon our deliverance from Hell fire, it alone would be thought cauſe enough to make us both patient, and thankfull; though the things we now delight in be taken from us. And ſure I am, nothing can be too much to endure; for thoſe pleaſures in Heaven which ſhall endure for ever. O that we could keepe faſt in our memories but theſe two things! and upon all occaſions make uſe of them; and conſider withall, that the leaſt mercy is beyond our beſt merit. And no better remedy for impatience, then to caſt up our receits, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with our deſervings. But ſecondly, <hi>Gods</hi> corrections, are his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions; his laſhes leſſons, his ſcourges ſchool-maſters, his chaſtiſements advertiſements to him; by feeling of ſmart he learnes to decline the cauſe. Yea, this hath taught him to fly from the workes of darkneſſe at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: and to conſider as well the bitterneſſe of what will follow, as the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a momentary pleaſure; and ſo cleared his ſight, that he can now diſcerne ſinne in all he thinkes, and ſpeakes, and does; for he is ever bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his wants, and weakneſſes; the hardneſſe of his heart, want of faith, &amp;c. Thirdly, it abundantly increaſeth his joy, and comfort: for admit Satan, and the world ſhould deprive him of all outward comforts at once: yet <hi>God</hi> at the ſame time, will ſupply the want of theſe; with comforts farre ſurpaſſing, and tranſcending them: as firſt, the aſſurance of the pardon of ſinne alone, is able to cleare all ſtormes of the minde: it teacheth miſery, as ſickneſſe, poverty, famine, impriſonment, infamy, &amp;c. even to laugh; for then let death happen, it matters not; when a Malefactor hath ſued out his pardon, let the Aſſizes come when they will, the ſooner the better. But to this is added the peace of
<pb n="M" facs="tcp:119873:13"/>conſcience, the marrow of all comforts; otherwiſe called, the peace of <hi>God,</hi> which paſſeth all underſtanding, and ſurpaſſeth all commending; for never did man finde pleaſure upon earth, like the ſweet teſtimony of an appeaſed conſcience, reconciled unto <hi>God,</hi> cleanſed by the blood of the Lambe, and quieted by the preſence of the Holy Ghoſt. As the Martyrs felt, who even clapt their hands for joy in the midſt of the flames; and were even raviſht, before they were permitted to dye: ſo great, and ſo paſſing all expreſſing is the peace and comfort of a good conſcience. Againe, thirdly, affliction bringeth with it the company of <hi>God</hi> himſelfe; <hi>I will be with you in tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.15. As when thoſe three were caſt into the fiery Furnace, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. there was preſently a fourth came to beare them company, and that was <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. to 27. and his preſence makes any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition comfortable were a man even in Hell it ſelfe. See more, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.52. And as his ſufferings abound, ſo his conſolation alſo aboundeth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. Indeed the unbeleever laughs more, but that laughter is onely the hypocriſie of mirth: they rejoyce in the face onely, and not in the heart: nor can it be ſolid comfort, except it hath his iſſue from a good conſcience; whereas Gods Word teacheth, and a good conſcience findeth, that even the teares of thoſe that pray, are ſweeter then the joyes of the Theater. But this is not all, for according to the tribulations laid upon him, and borne by him; ſhall the retribution of glory be proportioned. I might goe on and ſhew how it makes him pittifull, and compaſſionate to others: evills hath taught him to bemone all that affliction makes to groane; and ſundry the like which I may not here ſtand upon. And this is enough to ſhew, that affliction in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall makes much for his advantage; now ſee how he is a great gainer by each particular croſſe: As</p>
                  <p n="13">13. §. Firſt, let him fall into poverty, or have his goods and lands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcate, this ſhall not hurt but doe him good alſo: for he will not by ſinne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve his wants: poverty ſhall not conſtraine him to ſteale. He will not tell a lye (<hi>God</hi> aſſiſting him) though you would give him an houſe full of gold. Whereas let unbeleevers fall into the like condition, that they may maintaine themſelves; they will lye, deceive, ſteale, proſtitute their chaſtity, ſell their conſciences, and what not. Nor will he murmure, or repine againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; but beare it patiently and cheerefully: whereas unbeleevers will not onely murmure, and grievouſly complaine: but if <hi>God</hi> doe not anſwer them in every thing, they will take pleaſure in nothing: yea they will ſleight all his bleſſings, becauſe in one thing he croſſeth them. And as he will not be the worſe, ſo he will be much the better for it: for as he growes poore in temporalls, he will grow rich in ſpiritualls: his wants kill his wantonneſſe, his poverty checks his pride, &amp;c. It ſhall ſtir him up to prayer, weane him from the love of the world, approve his ſincerity, increaſe his faith, ſpirituall wiſedome, patience, and the like; ſo that let his enemies take all, ſo long as they cannot take <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Gods</hi> fatherly providence from him; he is well
<pb n="N" facs="tcp:119873:13"/>enough. But that's not all, for whatſoever he parts withall, be it Houſe, or Land, or any thing elſe; 'tis but as ſeed caſt into the ground: for he ſhall receive for it an hundreth fold more even in this world; and in the world to come life everlaſting, <hi>Marke</hi> 10.29.30. But</p>
                  <p n="14">14. §. Secondly, let him be caſt into Priſon and Bonds, <hi>God</hi> will doe him good by this alſo; even the Priſon ſhall prove a meanes of his ſpirituall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement, and he ſhall more freely injoy the preſence of his <hi>God.</hi> It ſhall make him with <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Sylas,</hi> ſing Pſalmes for joy at midnight; yea, he ſhall with that <hi>Seottiſh King</hi> in <hi>Mortimers</hi> hole, learne more of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in a ſhort time, then abroad he could in many yeares. And laſtly, it ſhall teach him for ever after, to remember them that are in Bonds, as if he were bound with them; and them which ſuffer adverſity, as if he ſuffered the ſame things with them.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. §. Thirdly, let his enemies ſlander him, <hi>God</hi> will cleare his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency; let them curſe him, the Lord will doe him good even for their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; let them deſpiſe and diſparage him, the Lord will ſo much the more honour him before the people: yea, the ſame men that formerly ſlighted, and rejected him, ſhall be forced to ſeeke and ſue unto him. Let an enemy ſcoffe at him for a fault, he will be the better for it to his dying day. His ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſcoffes bring him both to the knowledge, and likewiſe to the amendment of his faults. His being ſlighted ſhall quell his ambition, and vaine glory; and likewiſe exerciſe and improve his other graces. In fine, his enemies by their evill tongues ſhall beget in him a good, and holy life.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. §. Fourthly, let there be never ſo many plots laid to deſtroy him, he is in perpetuall ſafety; for the Lord not onely gives his <hi>Angells</hi> a charge over him, to keepe him in all his waies: but himſelfe is ever at hand to deliver him, and keepe him as the apple of his eye; ſo that all his enemies are not able to doe him hurt, for <hi>God</hi> is his helpe, and ſtrength, and deliverer; yea, <hi>God</hi> by his providence diſpoſeth of things ſo, that what in appearance, and what they contrived to be the meanes of his hurt, turnes to his great good; and what they intended for his deſtruction, becomes the only meanes of his preſervation. Againe, the Lord is more ſpecially preſent with him, when he is in the greateſt danger; that he may fight for him againſt his enemies, and give him victory over them; that he may ſuſtaine him when he faints, and crowne him when he overcomes; that he may be exact in taking notice of his ſufferings, count his wanderings, put his teares into his bottle, and enter all into his Regiſter. Nor is the <hi>Beleever</hi> more patient to put up wrongs, then <hi>God</hi> is ready to revenge them, and right him; and the reaſon is, <hi>Chriſt</hi> takes what is done to him, or any one of his members, as done to himſelf. And indeed he that deſpiſeth, traduceth, or any way wrongs him for his goodneſſe; his envie ſtrikes at the Image of <hi>God</hi> in him; by whoſe Spirit he both ſpeakes, and acts. And to murmure againſt any of <hi>Gods</hi> Meſſengers, (as thou art apt enough to doe) is to murmure againſt <hi>God</hi> himſelfe that ſent them; take
<pb n="O" facs="tcp:119873:14"/>notice of this, you that carry an aking tooth againſt every godly man you know. Neither ſhall Sorcery, or Witchcraft have the leaſt power to doe him hurt. In a word, there cannot ſo much as an haire fall from his head without the ſpeciall appointment of his heavenly Father, who will ſuffer nothing to befall him, but what ſhall make for his ſervants benefit, and his owne glory; for admit <hi>God</hi> gives his enemy leave, and power to kill him; he ſhall not hurt, but pleaſure him: as I ſhall ſhew when I come unto it.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. §. Fifthly, neither ſickneſſe, nor old age can hurt him: his fingers paine makes him not forget the health of his whole body; one dayes, or weeks ſicknes, makes him not forget many yeares health. He is not ſo ſenſible of a preſent diſtreſſe, nor ſo ingratefull for favours paſt; as not to remember many yeares injoyments, more then one weekes miſery. Yea, he conſiders that it is in great love, that <hi>God</hi> thus viſits him: that he dealeth mercifully with him, leaſt he ſhould fall from him and diſpaire; that he beateth him, leaſt he ſhould grow proud, and forget him, and ſo periſh. Beſides, he findes by experience, that as every other affliction rubs off ſome ruſt, melts off ſome droſſe, ſtraines out ſome corruption, &amp;c. ſo alſo that ſickneſſe cuts the very throat of all his vices; be it pride, luſt, covetouſneſſe, or the like; for the very worſt Feavour can come, does not more burne up his blood then his luſt; and together with ſweating out the ſurfits of Nature, at the poares of the body; he weepes out the ſinfull corruption of his nature, at the poares of his conſcience. And indeed <hi>God</hi> ſcourgeth his fleſh, to this end only, that his ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And the like of old age; his ſoule waxeth, as his body waineth, and he is wiſeſt to preſcribe, when his bones and ſinewes are weakeſt to execute.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. §. Sixthly, ſuppoſe he is in diſtreſſe of conſcience, and at the very brinke of deſpaire, expecting nothing but Hell and Damnation; ſuppoſe <hi>God</hi> hides his face, and ſeemes to have utterly forſaken him, and to reject his prayers; yea, ſuppoſe the terrours of <hi>God</hi> fight againſt him, and the Arrowes of the Almighty ſtick ſo faſt in him that the venome thereof hath drunke up his ſpirit; ſo that in his owne apprehenſion, <hi>God</hi> is become his mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as it fared with <hi>Job,</hi> yet all this is for his good, and ſhall doe him good; yea this extreame ſeverity of <hi>God</hi> argues favour, for nothing more uſuall then for <hi>God</hi> to worke joy out of feare, light out of darkneſſe, and to bring to the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> by the gates of Hell; and thus he deales with his deareſt darlings. When he meant to bleſſe <hi>Jacob,</hi> he wreſtles with him as an adverſary, even till he lamed him; when he meant to preferre <hi>Joſeph</hi> to the <hi>Throne,</hi> he threw him downe into the <hi>Dungeon;</hi> and to the Golden chaine about his neck, he laded him with Iron ones about his leggs. Nor would <hi>Chriſt</hi> cure <hi>Lazarus,</hi> till after he was dead, buried, and ſtunke againe: no queſtion to teach us, that we muſt be caſt downe by the Law, before we can be raiſed up by the Goſpell; and become fooles, before we can be truly wiſe. Nor hath he cauſe to feare, be his caſe never ſo deſperate; for <hi>God</hi> will meaſure
<pb n="P" facs="tcp:119873:14"/>his patience, and make it proportionable to his ſuffering; and equall his ſtrength to his temptations: his grace ſhall be ſufficient for him at the leaſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. and he that made the Veſſell, knowes her burden; and how to ballaſt her. The <hi>Buſh,</hi> which was a tipe of the <hi>Church</hi> conſumed not, all the while it burned with <hi>fire,</hi> becauſe <hi>God</hi> was in the midſt of it. The <hi>Anchor</hi> lyeth deepe, and is not ſeene: yet is the ſtay of all. The Bladder blowne, may float upon the floud; but cannot ſinke, nor ſtick in filthy mud. Sinne, Satan, and the world may diſturbe him, but they can never deſtroy him: his head <hi>Chriſt</hi> being above, he cannot be drowned; there can be no disjunction, unleſſe he could be pluckt from his armes that is Almighty: for his life is hid, with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>God, Col.</hi> 3.3. Beſides, if he ſuffers much, it ſhall not be long; if he ſuffers long, it ſhall not be much; if his ſorrowes be ſkarpe, they are the ſhorter. Grievous and ſore trialls laſt but for a ſeaſon, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6. a little while, <hi>John</hi> 16.16. yea but a moment, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. For a moment in mine anger ſaith <hi>God,</hi> I hid my face from thee, for a little ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: but with everlaſting mercy, have I had compaſſion on thee, <hi>Iſay</hi> 54.8. weeping may abide for a night, but joy commeth in the morning, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5. And it is ever ſeene, that his joy both ſucceeds, and exceeds his ſorrow: that his ſadneſſe ends in gladneſſe, and his ſorrow in ſinging. And the more grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous his exigent, the more glorious his advancement: But the laſt (which is the beſt) gaine of all: he growes more holy then ever, for like the Vine he bringeth forth the more, and better fruit for paring, and proyning and bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and though his outward man periſh, yet his inward man is renewed dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; even as a Lambe is much more lively, and nimble for ſhearing; theſe very tempeſtuous ſhowers, bring forth Spirituall flowers, and herbs in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. §. Seventhly, let Judgements be inflicted upon the whole Land: they ſhall not touch him, nor his family; he ſhall be ſingled out for mercy: Or if they doe, they ſhall be ſo ſanctified, that they ſhall rather pleaſure then hurt him. As if the Corn be cut down with the weeds, the one ſhall be carried into <hi>Gods</hi> Barne as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was, the other caſt into the fire like <hi>Dives;</hi> yea, every ſtroake in the Judgement ſhall be as a Monitor, and ſerve as a Sermon to him: when he ſees another ſtruck, he takes warning. For he will be put unto duty, even by the ſhadow of the wande.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. §. Eighthly, the ſtricteſt and ſevereſt Lawes if they be not contrary to <hi>Gods Law,</hi> have not power to ſmite him: for he does thoſe things unbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, which others can ſcarſe doe being compelled. Yea, the Law protects him againſt his enemies, who feare the Jayle more then they feare Hell; and ſtand more upon their ſilver, or their ſides ſmarting then upon their ſoules. Good <hi>Magiſtratas</hi> alſo, are the breath of his noſtrills, and protect him: while they take vengeance on them that doe ill. Yea they are the Miniſters of <hi>God</hi> for his welth, and bound to ſee him righted; when he receives wrong in his perſon, goods, or good name.</p>
                  <pb n="Q" facs="tcp:119873:15"/>
                  <p n="21">21. §. Ninthly, his very ſinnes, and infirmities by <hi>Gods</hi> grace doe worke his good; and he is by much the better for them: for he will from hence grow more holy. Yea, he gaines ſtrength by every fall: for hence iſſues deeper humiliation, ſtronger hatred of ſinne, freſh indignation againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, more experience of his hearts deceitfulneſſe, renewed reſolutions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſinne be brought under: it makes him more earneſt with <hi>God</hi> by prayer, to keepe a more carefull watch over himſelfe; to pitty others more, and cenſure them leſſe when they offend, or are over-taken: to reſt wholly upon the aſſiſtance of <hi>Gods</hi> Spirit; and to aſcribe all glory to him; of whom what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he hath he holds. True, his offending <hi>God</hi> brings much miſery upon him: and <hi>God</hi> ſeemes to have left him, and to reject his prayers and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation: but at length, and ſo ſoone as the poore ſoule ceaſeth to doe evill, and learnes to doe well: the Lord repenteth him of the evill; and not only delivers him, but returnes with the greater intereſt of joy and felicity. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Lord lets him know what it is to loſe his favour, and makes him tugg hard by prayer, and to perſevere a long time in knocking, and asking: but at length he will be ſure to give him what he deſires, or that which is better for him; for the prayer of faith, from the knees of humility, and a broken heart will conquer even the Conqueror. Indeed, the caſe may be ſuch that he cannot pray, or not to purpoſe; as in time of ſickneſſe, by reaſon of the extremity of paine: but then he can ſend to the <hi>Congregations,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them to pray for him. Beſides, all his former prayers, and meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe ſerve to ayde him in his laſt ſtraits; and meet together in the center of his extremity: yeelding though not ſenſible reliefe, yet ſecret be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to his ſoule. Yea (which is beſt of all) he hath the benefit of <hi>Chriſts</hi> interceſſion in Heaven, and of the prayers of all the <hi>Saints</hi> on <hi>earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="22">22. §. Tenthly, the malice of Satan, ſhall make much for his good: for if Satan be ſent to buffet him, as he did <hi>Paul;</hi> or to winnow him, as he would have done <hi>Peter;</hi> it is that he may not be exalted: his malice ſhall prove the occaſion of much good to him, as it did to the <hi>inceſtious Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian;</hi> or if <hi>God</hi> lets him looſe upon him, as he did upon <hi>Job:</hi> it ſhall but advance the glory of <hi>God,</hi> manifeſt this Beleevets patience, occaſion his owne ſhame, &amp;c. ſo the Devill ſhall be over-ſhot in his owne Bow, and wounded with his owne Weapon. And ſo it is, that to all whom <hi>God</hi> hath any intereſt in, this <hi>Scorpion</hi> ſhall prove a Medecine againſt the ſting of the <hi>Scorpion.</hi> For though he ayme at deſpaire, and deſtruction; yet <hi>God</hi> aymes at humiliation, and converſion; yea at conſolation, and ſalvation: and when the Sinner is ſufficiently humbled, Satan ſhall be caſhiered? that <hi>Horſe-leach</hi> ſhall be taken off, when he hath ſufficiently abated the viſcous and ſuperfluous blood; ſo that he ſhall be healed by wounding, exalted by humbling; Satan ſhall helpe him to the deſtruction of his fleſh, (his corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and the edification of his ſoule.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. §. Eleventhly, Death, the laſt and ſtrongeſt enemy of all, ſhall doe
<pb n="R" facs="tcp:119873:15"/>him the greateſt good of all. He may be killed, but he cannot be hurt, nor conquered: for even Death, that Fiend is to him a friend: like the <hi>Red Sea</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that put them over to the <hi>Land of Promiſe;</hi> whiles it drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their enemies. It is his bridge from woe to glory, for dying he ſleepes, and ſleeping he reſts from all the travailes of a toyleſome life, to live in joy, and bliſſe for evermore. It is to him the end of all ſorrowes, and the beginning of his everlaſting joyes. The ceſſation of all trouble, a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedias for all diſeaſes, the extinction of ſinne, the deliverance from ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, a reſcue from Satan, the quiet reſt of the body, and infranchiſement of the ſoule.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. §. Thus as the unbeleever, and diſobedient is curſed in every thing, and where ever he goes, and in whatſoever he does: curſed in the <hi>City,</hi> and curſed alſo in the Field; curſed in the fruit of his body, and in the fruit of his ground, and in the fruit of his Cattell: curſed when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in, and curſed alſo when he goeth out: curſed in this life, and curſed in the life to come; as is at large expreſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. So the Beleever, that obeyes the voyce of the Lord, ſhall be bleſſed in every thing he does; where ever he goes, and in whatſoever befalls him. As <hi>God</hi> promiſeth in the former part of the ſame Chapter, and as I have proved in the eleaven fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Sections. Yea, <hi>God</hi> will bleſſe all that belong unto him, for his Children, and poſterity, yea many generations after him ſhall fare the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his ſake: yea the very place where he dwells, perhaps the whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> he lives in. Where as many, yea multitudes, even an whole <hi>Army;</hi> yea his Childrens Children unto the third and fourth generation; farre the worſe for a wicked man- and an unbeleever. Beſides, his prayers ſhall profit many: for he is more prevalent with <hi>God,</hi> to take away a Judgement from a People, or a Nation, then a thouſand others. And he counts it a ſinne to ceaſe praying for his greateſt, and moſt malitious enemies; though they like fooles, would (if they durſt, or were permitted) cut him off: and all the race of <hi>Gods</hi> people; which is as if one with his hatchet ſhould cut off the bough of a Tree upon which he ſtandeth. For they are beholding to Beleevers, for their very lives: yea it is for their ſakes, and becauſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Chriſts Church</hi> is not yet accompliſht, that they are out of Hell. But to goe on, as all things <hi>(viz.)</hi> poverty, impriſonment, ſlander, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſickneſſe, death, temporall Judgements, ſpirituall diſſertions, yea even ſinne, and Satan himſelfe) ſhall turne together for the beſt unto thoſe that love <hi>God,</hi> as you have ſeene. So all things ſhall turne together for the worſt unto them that hate <hi>God;</hi> as all unbeleevers doe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. <hi>John</hi> 15.18. even the mercy of <hi>God,</hi> and the meanes of grace, ſhall prove their bane, and inhance their damnation; yea <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, that only <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> who is a Saviour to all beleevers, ſhall be a juſt revenger to all unbeleevers: and bid the one, Depart yee curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devill and his Angells: while he ſhall ſay unto the other, Come yee bleſſed
<pb n="S" facs="tcp:119873:16"/>of my Father, inherit the <hi>Kingdome, &amp;c.</hi> Which being ſo, how doth it concerne all, to ſee that they are Beleevers? Wouldeſt thou then have it fare ſo with thee? Wouldeſt thou have thy very poyſons turned into cordialls? thy terrors, changed into pleaſures? and thy greateſt evills made beneficiall unto thee? Wouldeſt thou be looſed from the chaines of thy ſinnes, and delivered from the chaines of plagues? Wouldeſt thou have the ſame <hi>Coriſt,</hi> with his precious Blood to free thee, that ſhall with his word ſentence others? As who would not, except Satan hath ſtrangely bewitcht him? If thou wouldeſt, I ſay, then learne of this <hi>Beleever,</hi> imitate him in what hath been declared, and what I ſhall further rehearſe touching his knowledge, beleefe, and life; for I have onely brake the thread of my Diſcourſe, to let in this uſe in way of a Parenthaſis, which otherwiſe comming too late muſt have been left out; and now I returne to finiſh or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the fore-going Character, for thereunto may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as followeth.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. §. He loves, and feares, and beleeves, and ſerves the Lord, and ſeekes his glory, and the good of others in every thing; at leaſt he deſires, and endeavours ſo to doe. He will omit no opportunity of doing good, nor doe evill though he hath opportunity. He remembers his vow in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and is carefull to performe what he then promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and ſo farre as he comes ſhort of his duty, ſo farre forth he will be humbled. He tempteth not to evill, but draweth all he can to goodneſſe. He will behave himſelfe honeſtly, and unblameably before thoſe among whom he lives: that he may not diſhonour God, nor offend either thoſe that are within, or thoſe that are without. He will never ſuffer baſe thoughts of God, to finde harbour in his heart deale he never ſo harſhly with him; being more prone to complaine of his ſinne, then of his puniſhment:
<pb n="T" facs="tcp:119873:16"/>for he will turne his eyes inward, and read his ſinne in his puniſhment; and inſtead of murmuring for the few things he wants, be thankfull for the many things he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes. Whereas others that are unbeleevers, will doe ſomething for God, when it makes for their owne ends, he will ſuffer for him; and hold out in his workes where Satan dwells, and keeps his throne. And what they doe for feare of the Law, he does for love of the Goſpell. As who are <hi>Beleever,</hi> indeed, is onely knowne where the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of godlineſſe is in contempt; where a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in name onely, will ſcoffe at a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> indeed: for in ſuch times, many will ſuperſtitiouſly adore the <hi>Crucifix;</hi> that are enemies to the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and worſhip the dead <hi>Saints</hi> in a cold profeſsion; while they worry he living, in a cruell perſecution For <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſtoned by many that are called <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> though no otherwiſe then the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Images are called gods. But the Beleever, as he will not go on in an evil way, though flattered by never ſo good ſucceſſe: ſo he will not be diſcouraged in a good way; though he meets with ill ſucceſſe becauſe he is more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to pleaſe God then men Nature is like glaſſe bright but brittle: the reſolved <hi>Chriſtian</hi> like <hi>Gold;</hi> which if we rub it, or beat it, or melt it: it will endure the Teaſt, the touch, the hammer, and ſtill ſhine more orient A <hi>true beleever</hi> having once acknowledged the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: will not after turne from the holy Commandment. Like the Dog that returnes to his vomit, or the Sow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the mire. Againe, he will not come to his ends by unlawfull meanes, he ſeekes not to <hi>Witches, Wizards,</hi> or <hi>South-ſayers</hi> in his diſtreſſe; or to be reſolved of his doubts: but to <hi>Gods Word,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and to <hi>God</hi> himſelfe by prayer; and in praying to him, he deſires not outward bleſsings ſo much as <hi>Gods</hi> bleſsing upon them: he deſireth not ſo much food, and
<pb n="V" facs="tcp:119873:17"/>rayment; as that God will give them power to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, warme, and comfort him; knowing that except that be granted, they cannot of themſelves doe it. And ſo of riches, wiſedome, &amp;c. He deſires not ſo much a great eſtate, as a contended minde. He deſires not riches, that he may lay it out on his pleaſures; yea he knowes that God will not give i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he abuſe his gifts And as he prayes for Gods bleſsing, ſo he neglect not to uſe the meanes. When he hath attained his end or receives any mercy, whether it be riches, or o her gifts, victory or the like: he aſcribes not the praiſe thereof to his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or induſtry but wholly and onely to the free mercy of God in Chriſt. Now for concluſion of this point, wouldeſt thou know whether thou art a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever or no? this will infallibly informe thee: thy faith in the Commands will breed obedience, in the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings feare, in the promiſes comfort.</p>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Here ends the new inſerted matter.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <p>Errata.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page</hi> 22. line 30. for <hi>Prieſts,</hi> read <hi>Princes.</hi> line 9. in page E, for <hi>deing</hi> right being, line 36. croſſe out the full point.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>§. 38. He is zealous to admoniſh, reclaime, and reduce ſuch as go aſtray; and to ſave thoſe among whom he lives, out of duty and thankfulneſſe to <hi>God,</hi> and his Redeemer, and out of love to them.</p>
               <p>§. 39. He reformes his family, and ſets up <hi>Gods</hi> Worſhip therein, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the duties of Prayer, reading, repeating, &amp;c. and inſtructing his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſervants.</p>
               <p>§. 40. He makes conſcience of ſanctifying the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and ſees that all under him doe the ſame: He will not give liberty to his ſervants upon the Lords day, to doe what they liſt.</p>
               <p>§. 41. He is hated of the world for goodnes, and ſuffers ſome way for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> at leaſt, he is evill ſpoken of for well doing, and rejoyceth therein, or in whatſoever he ſuffers; well conſidering, that all his ſufferings in this life are not worthy that glory he ſhall injoy in the next.</p>
               <p>§. 42. He is juſt and upright in his dealings, and deſires to pay every one his due; he will not borrow without care to pay againe, as doe the wicked, for which they are branded by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.21. He will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine wages, or worke mens hire, (a crying ſinne that this City groanes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) He is faithfull to ſuch as put him in truſt: if a ſervant, he perloynes not; nor deceives in going to market; nor did ever any but hipocrite pretend care of piety towards <hi>God,</hi> and yet be unmercifull, and unjuſt to men; yea, it is Devill like, and double damnation; to pretend Piety, and intend Villany, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. And indeed, our faith in <hi>Chriſt</hi> is beſt ſeene in our faithfulneſſe to men; our inviſible beliefe by our viſible life. O that all hypocriticall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors would try themſelves by this touchſtone, and conſequently either he what they ſeeme (reall Chriſtians) or ſeeme as they are (none of <hi>Chriſts</hi>) ſo ſhould they not ſhame Religion by profeſſing it; whereas now, they make the way of truth evill ſpoken of; yea, for their ſakes the name of goodneſſe is blaſphemed all the day long, and an ill report raiſed upon them that ſerve <hi>God</hi> in truth; yea, they have made our ſavour to ſtinke in the eyes of all the people, and put a Sword into the hands of prophane men to ſlay us; as wofull experience ſhewes; for by reaſon of ſuch, how doe the Devill and his Limbes triumph over the religious; yea, the Saints are not only reproached, the truth diſgraced, and Religion it ſelfe ſcandalized; but this gives occaſion to others to blaſpheame <hi>God,</hi> and to doubt whether all Divinity be not meere Policy, and the Scriptures a Fable, whereby millions are ſo hardened, that they even proteſt againſt their owne converſion; which being ſo, if you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119873:6"/>either love <hi>God</hi> or his people, if you either care for other mens ſoules, or your owne, remove this ſtumbling block, and no longer deceive your ſelves; for though he that is not a true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> may be juſt, yet he that is not juſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be a true <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 43. He will firſt labour to informe, and then hearken to, and obey the voyce of conſcience together with the motions of <hi>Gods</hi> Spirit; conſider ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers caſe by his own, and in a good meaſure do to all others as he would have others doe by him.</p>
               <p>§. 44. And as he is juſt in getting, ſo he is neither profuſe in ſpending, nor backward (according to his ability) in releeving <hi>Chriſts</hi> members for his ſake, but will give back a conſiderable part of all he hath to <hi>God;</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that he is onely a Steward (not an Owner) of what he doth poſſeſſe.</p>
               <p>§. 45. He denies ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and lives ſoberly and chaſtly in this preſent world, keeping the members of his body holy; for if he hath not the giſt of continency, he will marry; his ſpeech is not lewd, or obſcene, nor uſeth he any laſcivious behaviour, nor does he take liberty to gaze upon beautifull women.</p>
               <p>§. 46. He is neither Drunkard nor Glutton, he neither tarries long at the Wine, nor goes often to it, as is the cuſtome of too many; indeed, whether they be <hi>Chriſtians</hi> or no I cannot eaſily be ſatified.</p>
               <p>§. 47. It is not his manner to curſe be he never ſo much provoked, neither will he take the name of <hi>God</hi> in vaine, but reverently uſe his titles in his talke; much leſſe will he ſweare by his Name, except upon urgent occaſion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lawfully called to it before a Magiſtrate; leaſt of all dare he ſweare by, or invocate that which is no god; namely, by any Creature, or Idoll, which carnall men ignorantly call petty oathes: No, but as he will not ſweare, ſo he feares an Oath.</p>
               <p>§. 48. He will ſpeake the truth from his heart, and not willingly and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditately either lye, or equivocate, much leſſe will he allow himſelfe in it, or ſeeke to defend it; for ſuch as will doe ſo, have not as yet paſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Birth.</p>
               <p>§. 49. In bearing witneſſe he will ſpeake the whole truth impartially, without fearing or favouring either Party; that is, as well what makes for the Defendant, though an enemy, as for the Plaintiffe being his friend, or Maſter; neither will he conceale a wicked device, when by revealing the ſame it may be prevented.</p>
               <p>§. 50 If a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> he will not be partiall in any cauſe, nor will he either for feare or favour doe any thing againſt the truth; or give ſentence againſt his Conſcience, or uſe his power in favour of the wicked; but be juſt in ſhewing mercy, ſevere to the evill, cheriſhing and protecting the good.</p>
               <p>§. 51. He is not implacable, nor will he revenge himſelfe on an enemy, though he hath power in his hand to doe it; but ſhut his eares and heart in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119873:6"/>this, and other caſes againſt Satans temptations; yea, upon the leaſt change, he can forgive him as heartily as he defires <hi>God</hi> ſhould forgive him, yea, he loves and wiſhes well, and can willingly doe good to them that doe evill to him; even deſiring his greateſt enemies converſion, together with his proſperity. He rejoyceth not at anothers fall, but is grieved both for their ſins and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; nor is he grieved at any ones good, eſpecially at his gifts, and the graces of <hi>Gods</hi> Spirit in him.</p>
               <p>§. 52. He hath learnt (from <hi>Gods</hi> dealing with him) to be mercifull, as his heavenly Father is mercifull, even to his Beaſt. Nor doe any that reſemble <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (but Satan and Antichriſt, as partaking of the Devills nature) ſport themſelves in Beare-baiting, Dogge, or Cock-fighting, hunting of tame Ducks, and the like; or if ſo, they are not well verſt in Chriſtianity; as for ſuch as are cruell to their ſervants, I marvaile how they can expect that their maſter in Heaven ſhould be mercifull to them; and certainely, ſhould they be deprived from ever having the helpe or benefit of ſervants, (as good Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> once ſerved a Butcher and his Wife, for their cruelty to a poore Girle they kept) they would in a ſhort time learne to be both wiſer and better.</p>
               <p>§. 53. Whereas many love peace, but regard not truth; and others are all for truth, without caring for peace: he together with truth loves, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and labours to have a lawfull peace with all men, and ſo ſeekes it, that he will ſuffer rather then doe wrong; and to avoyd offence, he will be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled in indifferent things: As <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave him an example, when he paid Pole-money.</p>
               <p>§. 54. He is not glad of pretences againſt obeying the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but will obey authority as the ordinance of <hi>God;</hi> and be ſubject more out of conſcience then feare, as placed by <hi>God</hi> over him; and to all their Lawes, if they croſſe not <hi>Gods</hi> Law: for otherwiſe he will loſe his liberty: part with the right hand of profit, and the right eye of pleaſure; yea, loſe his life rather then a good conſcience, and ſinne againſt <hi>God;</hi> for he will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey <hi>God,</hi> to obey great ones.</p>
               <p>§. 55. He is not the worſe, or prouder for proſperity, or outward bleſtings, but the better, and more thankfull for them; he is bettered alſo by affliction, and makes a gaine of his loſſes; and being in diſtreſſe as he prayes for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſo he is accordingly thankfull when delivered; yea, he will make vowes, and ſo promiſe amendment, that he is as carefull to performe the ſame when he is delivered, which a wicked man never does.</p>
               <p>§. 56. He ſeekes <hi>God</hi> in all he does, and acknowledges him in all he either receives or ſuffers; he obſerves the ſeverall paſſages of his Providence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acknowledging all things to be ordered thereby, and that it extendeth to the leaſt haire on his head; hath a comfortable experience of his diſpoſing all, to worke for the beſt unto him; admires the ſame, and his goodneſſe therein, and is accordingly thankfull for it; yea, he keepes a Record, or Regiſter of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119873:7"/>
                  <hi>Gods</hi> ſpeciall mercies and deliverances, and of his owne often and great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, and not ſeldome meditates thereon; neither does he murmure when he wants any thing, as moſt of our ignorant poore doe, whoſe whole life, language, and religion is nought elfe but a continued act of mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and murmuring; perhaps they want many things for their bodies, becauſe they ſlight whatſoever is offered to their ſoules; and becauſe <hi>God</hi> the Giver is not in all their thoughts except to blaſpheame him, and to ſpend his Day in the Devills ſervice, for they never minde how <hi>God</hi> hath appointed it his Market-day for their ſoules; now theſe brutiſh Animals are very ſenſible if they want never ſo little, and for that they murmure; but they injoy mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of mercies which they never cordially give thankes for; and I wiſh they were often put in minde how many thouſand <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were deſtroyed in the Wilderneſſe, onely for that grievous ſinne of murmuring, though their ſtraites and extreamities were farre greater; but as good blow in the duſt as ſpeake to theſe; and as they have no reaſon, ſo they will heare none, onely ſuch as truly feare <hi>God</hi> know that he owes them nothing; yea, what ever they injoy on this ſide Hell, they thinke themſelves unworthy of it.</p>
               <p>§ 57. He is not raſhly cenſorious, but judgeth of things, actions, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, (not as they are in the worlds repure, but) as they are in <hi>Gods</hi> account, and as he in his Word allowes or condemnes them; he cenſures none for things indifferent; but you muſt be able to alleadge the violation of ſome Law: much leſſe will he mocke or deſpiſe a man for his poverty, or any naturall defect; as for judging anothers thoughts to be evill when he cannot tax his life, or making ill conſtructions of good actions, or ſleighting and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraging them, or thinking the vorſe of a man for having of a tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he utterly abhorres. He is not eaſily ſuſpicions without juſt cauſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will he willingly wreſt mens words, or miſconſter their meanings, but take their ſayings and doings in the beſt ſence. He will not hearken to tale-beaters, nor is he apt to beleeve an evill report without good ground; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will he condemne a man without hearing him ſpeake. He never deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines of any ones finall eſtate be he never ſo wicked, well knowing, that <hi>God</hi> may change his heart in a moment; neither will he conclude one to be a wicked man, or an hypocrite for appearances, or moates, or ſome ſuddaine eruptions, or common infirmities, or for ſinnes before converſion, or for this or that ſingle act of groſſe impiety; when the maine tenor and courſe of his life beſides is a continuall current of honeſty and goodneſſe; though he may ſuſpend his good opinion in caſe of ſome unexpected miſdemeanour, or for leſſer evills, either affected or oftea repeated. He is tender hearted, and can beare with the infirmities of the weake, and is ready to cheriſh them that are caſt downe. He does not expect a full growth of Grace in the Cradle of a mans converſion; yea, he yeelds the beſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (in this their ſtate of imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) their graynes of allowance, as <hi>our Saviour</hi> did to his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119873:17"/>
               <p>§. 58. He is not of a reprobate judgement in thinking good evill, and evill good; neither hath he a baſe eſteeme of <hi>Gods</hi> people, and their wayes, as it fares with our ſcoffing adverſaries, who looke upon zeale and holineſſe with the Devills ſpectacles; nor ſo farre from being holy himſelfe that he hates holineſſe in others, or ſo ſtupidly ſottiſh as the rude rabble; who will profeſſe that they love <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yet hate all ſuch as any way reſemble him. He will take heed of perſecuting the godly either with hand or tongue; and as he will not condemne the juſt, ſo he will not juſtifie the wicked, nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour them.</p>
               <p>§. 59. He rejoyceth when the righteous are exalted, and grieves when the wicked beare rule. He is no enemy to reformation, but earneſtly deſires the ſame, and furthers it all he can.</p>
               <p>§. 60. He is ſo farre from taking offence when none is given, that he will not be offended when offences come; as at the ſcandalous lives of Profeſſors, or at the multitude of Hereſies that are daily broached though they grieve his very ſoule; but when ſtrange things happen, he makes a wholſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction thereof.</p>
               <p>§. 61. He cannot heare <hi>God</hi> blaſphemed or diſhonoured without being moved thereat, yea, he is as heartily vexed for any diſhonour done to him, as for any diſgrace offered to himſelfe. He hath an holy care and endeavour in all places and companies, to walke ſo as he may win glory to <hi>God,</hi> honour his profeſſion, and give no offence or occaſion to the enemies of <hi>God</hi> to ſpeake evill of him; he acknowledgeth all good to come from <hi>God,</hi> and that all glory is to be given to him; and accordingly endeavours to honour and ſerve him with his riches, wiſedome, and what other gifts or abilities he hath; neither is he dumbe in publiſhing his praiſe, nor backward to juſtifie him in his judgements. He will not worſhip an Image, or <hi>God</hi> in the Image; he ſeldome ſells things tending to Idolatry, or any other ſinne, or uſes lots in ſporting. He feares <hi>God,</hi> and feares ſin, and this diſpelleth in him all other falſe, fond, and fooliſh feares, which others that are voyd of the feare of <hi>God,</hi> are grievouſly and perpetually perplexed withall; as namely, he fears not that his ſerving of <hi>God</hi> wil prove his undoing, he neither feares nor obſerves the flying of Fowles the ſigns of Heaven, the ſight of a live Snake, the croſſing of an Hare, the croak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Raven, the ſcritching of an Owl, the howling of a Dog, the dreaming of Gardens, green Ruſhes, or dead friends; to eat an Egge in Lent, or fleſh on a Friday never racks his Conſcience; whether the Crow cries even or odde in a morning, or whether he leaves the Croſſe on his right or left hand as he goes; whether it be Childermas Day or not, when he takes a Journey, or undertakes any buſineſſe, or whether the Salt-ſeller falls from or towards him, it is all one to him; nor does ſtumbling at a threſhold preſage any evill to him at all; he never croſſes his breaſt, nor ſprinckles his fate when he is to goe abroad, nor nailes Horſe-ſhooes at his doore, and yet ſpeeds never the worſe; neither old Wives, nor Starres are his Counſellors; a Night-ſpell is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119873:18"/>none of his guide, nor Charmes his <hi>Phyſitian; Erra Pater</hi> is no part of his Creed; neither weares he Ammulets, or Paraſelſian Characters about his neck, you ſhall never heare him talke of luckey handſell, and Fortune to him is an aſſe; Buggs never fright him, nor Fairies pinch him, neither will he put confidence in any ſuch ſuperſtitious and devilliſh ſopperies, as the ignorant and ſuperſtitious doe; no, he will not be beholding to the King of Hell for a ſhooe-tye.</p>
               <p>§. 62. He ſeekes the good, and to preſerve the peace of the place he lives in, and can comfort himſelfe with this, that in his very Calling and publicke imployments, his aime and indeavour is not more at profit or credit then at the glory of <hi>God,</hi> and good of others; he hath an humble and publick ſpirit, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in doing good offices, and is active to pleaſure others, and can make him ſelfe a ſervant to all that ſtand in need of him.</p>
               <p>§. 63. Nor is he partiall in his obedience, but univerſall, making conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of every duty, and all that <hi>God</hi> commands; the firſt Table as well as the ſecond, and the ſecond as well as the firſt; framing his will to <hi>Gods</hi> Will in every thing, even labouring to be perfect, and holy, as his Father in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is; and to imitate <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be conformed to his likeneſſe, and to be holy as he was in all parts of his converſation; and that at all times, and in all companies, as conſcientious alone and in private, where <hi>God</hi> onely ſees him, as if his greateſt enemy, or all the world did behold him; he hath a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit without guile, and is more deſirous to be good then ſo accounted, and more ſeekes the power of godlineſſe then the ſhew of it; and therefore keepes a narrower watch over his very thoughts then any other can doe over his actions; and is accordingly grieved for them. He makes conſcience of the ſmalleſt things required or forbidden in the Word; and is as carefull to ſhun the very occaſions of ſinne, or leaſt appearances, or firſt motions of ſinne as actuall ſinne it ſelfe; not daring to gratifie Satan in committing the leaſt ſinne, or neglect <hi>God</hi> in omitting the ſmalleſt precept.</p>
               <p>§. 64. He does not ſerve <hi>God</hi> by the precepts of men, nor feare his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure for breaking their traditions; neither does he think himſelfe ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by outward performances, as doe our Formaliſts and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at large, who ſtand more upon circumſtance then ſubſtance, and upon outward privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges then inward graces; but he ſerves <hi>God</hi> in ſpirit, according to <hi>Chriſts Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> for he lives and beleeves, and heares, and invocates, and hopes, and feares, &amp; loves, and worſhips <hi>God</hi> in ſuch manner as his Word preſcribes, without addition or demination; neither does he follow the examples of the greateſt number, or the greateſt men, or the greateſt Schollers, becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath plainely told him, That few of either ſort (compared with the multitude) ſhall be ſaved; of which ſmall number he ſtrives to be.</p>
               <p>§. 65. All which he performes with cheerefulneſſe, being ever willing and ready to doe good; and in ſincerity and ſimplicity, with a ſingle heart, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out buy ends, as loving righteouſneſſe and mercy, and doing good duties
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119873:18"/>meerly out of love to <hi>God</hi> and goodneſſe, and becauſe <hi>God</hi> commands them that he may be glorified, and others edified thereby; yea he would doe what he is able out of love to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> though himſelfe ſhould never have credit not benefit by it here, nor hereafter; earneſtly deſiring grace that he might more honour him, and grieving that he can performe no better ſervice to ſo good a Maſter. He will not (as too many moſt ſordidly doe) take liberty to ſin, becauſe <hi>God</hi> is mercifull, and forbeares to execute judgement ſpeedily; or deferre his repentance, becauſe the <hi>Thiefe</hi> upon the Croſſe was heard at the laſt hour: but he will even therefore the more feare him becauſe he is mercifull; and therefore be holy, becauſe he is not under the Law, but under grace.</p>
               <p>§. 66. And laſtly, having thus done, and performed his utmoſt, not to merit by it, but to expreſſe his thankfulneſſe to him that hath done, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſuffered ſo much for him; he confeſſeth himſelfe an unprofitable ſervant, and that in all he comes farre ſhort of performing his duty; yea, he ackcowledgeth, that it were juſt for <hi>God</hi> eternally to condemne him. Well may he be comforted by the graces which <hi>God</hi> hath given him, as an earneſt penny of thoſe eternall Manſions in Heaven; but he will not be exalted by them becauſe they are not his graces, but the Graces of <hi>God</hi> in him, and wrought by his Spirit: yea, he ſo abhorres to attribute or aſcribe ought to doing, that he counts his very righteouſneſſe no better then filthy raggs, aſcribing every good thought, word, and action which proceeds from him to Free Grace, for he lookes back to the rock out of which he was hewne, and is not onely humbled thereby, but forced with an holy admiration to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at the marvellous and extraordinary change which <hi>God</hi> hath wrought in him, and alſo inſtructed to truſt onely to <hi>Chriſts</hi> obedience, in whom onely our good workes are accepted, and for whom alone they are rewarded. To ſhut up all, he indeavours ſo to live as if there were no <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and ſo to dye as if there were no <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 67. Onely it remaines that you looke your ſelves in this <hi>glaſſe,</hi> and try your ſelves by this <hi>touchſtone;</hi> for though others may give a ſhrewd gheſſe, yet the Mother knowes beſt whether the Childe be like the Father or no; and the ſignes of Salvation are to be ſought in our ſelves, as the cauſe in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> our Juſtification is to be proved by the fruits of our Sanctification, and though faith alone juſtifieth, yet juſtifying faith is never alone, but ever accompanied with ſpirituall graces, the beauties of the ſoule, and good workes the beauty of graces; yea, they are as inſeparable as the root and the ſap, the <hi>Sunne</hi> and its light; and as <hi>Fire</hi> may be diſcerned by heat, and life by motion, ſo a mans faith may be diſcerned by the fruits of it. Nor can any one be deceived except he deſires to deceive himſelfe, for every particular man is either the Childe of <hi>God,</hi> or the Childe of the Devill, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath it, for there is not a meane betwixt them; and there be more differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces betweene the Children of <hi>God</hi> and the Children of the Devill, then there are between Men and Beaſts, whereof I have named not a few; for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119873:19"/>you may find the one (herein ſet forth) to ſpeake, think, or doe, the other does the contrary; and to have the true Character of an unbeleever you need but read this Character of a true Beleever backward, underſtand all by the rule of contraries and be ſatisfied; I ſpeake this to Naturians onely, for the regenerate man knowes the one to be ſo by what he is, and the other by what he hath been; neither is there one of all theſe ſignes or characters but each experienced <hi>Chriſtian</hi> findes it in ſome degree written in his heart, as his conſcience can beare me witneſſe. And would you know whether you belong to <hi>Chriſt?</hi> This will informe you, you will (by helpe from above) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring into captivity every thought and thing to the obedience of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.5. 1 John, 2.4. but ſo have not you in the leaſt ſo long as you love not, or any way oppoſe the people of <hi>God;</hi> for the very firſt part of converſion is, to love them that love <hi>God,</hi> 1 John, 3.10. yea in reaſon, if the Image of <hi>God</hi> by faith were repaired in thee, thou couldeſt not but be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with thoſe that are like thy ſelfe. And what ſaith St. <hi>John,</hi> He that pretends intereſt in <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and keepeth not his Commandements, is a lyar, and the truth is not in him; 1 <hi>John,</hi> 2.4. and in the third Chapter and eighth Verſe he affirmes plainly, That all wilfull ſinners are the Devills ſervants. And indeed, let men flatter themſelves, or pretend what they will; it cannot be denyed but the fruit tells beſt the name of the <hi>Tree;</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation above all ſhewes who carries the bridle of the will, whether <hi>God</hi> or Satan: and did not men purpoſely ſhut their eyes, and ſtop their eares, and harden their owne hearts, leaſt they ſhould ſee, and heare, and ſo be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelfe ſpeakes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.15. they could not but know that the whole <hi>Bible</hi> beates upon this: It is Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> everlaſting rule, <hi>Rom</hi> 6.16. Yea are his ſervants to whom ye obey. And Saint <hi>Peters</hi> infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Doctsrine, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. Of whom a man is overcome, unto him he is in bondage. And Saint <hi>Johns,</hi> In this are the Children of <hi>God</hi> knowne, and the Children of the Devill; whoſoever doth not righteouſneſſe is not of <hi>God,</hi> but of the Devill, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8, 10. And after this manner does our <hi>Saviour</hi> reaſon with the <hi>Jewes, John</hi> 8.33. to 48. See then whoſe commands ye doe, <hi>Gods,</hi> or Satans; if Satans, then ſaith Saint <hi>John,</hi> Let no man deceive you through vaine words, for he onely that doth righteouſneſſe is righteous, and he that doth unrighteouſneſſe is of the Devill, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.7, 8. wherefore if thou art a common Drunkard, or a continuall Swearer, or an uſuall compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Harlots, or an accuſtomary Deceiver, or a frequent ſlanderer of thy Neighbour, or an open and common Sabbath-breaker, or canſt thou boaſt of ſinne and miſchiefe, or defend it? If thou makeſt no conſcience of Praying in thy Family; if thou calleſt evill good, and good evill; if thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thy Brother for doing that which is good, as <hi>Caine</hi> did <hi>Abel;</hi> if <hi>Iſmael</hi>-like thou mockeſt, or <hi>Cham</hi>-like thou ſcoffeſt at the religious, or uſeſt bitter ieſts againſt them, though it be under the notion of Round-heads, Puritanes, Sectaries, Black-coates; or the like; if thou raiſeſt ſlanders of them, or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119873:19"/>them being raiſed; if thou doſt rejoyce at the ſecret infirmities of the godly, or open ſcandalls of Hypocrites; if thou doſt carpe and fret againſt the Word, refuſing to heare it, or withſtandeſt the preaching of it; if being a Miniſter thou diſgrafeſt or revileſt the godly in thy preaching, ſo making ſad the hearts of the righteous, or juſtifyeſt the wicked, ſo ſtrengthening them in their evill courſes by preaching unto them peace; if thou haſt a baſe eſteeme of <hi>Gods</hi> people and their wayes, and thinkeſt the worſe of a man for ſcrupling ſmall matters; if thou makeſt Religion a cloake for villany, if thou doſt borrow, or run in debt without care to pay againe; if thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt in cruelty, if thou takeſt no care to provide for thine own family; if thou hadſt rather the wicked ſhould beare rule then the godly; if thou art an enemy to reformation, if thou hadſt rather diſobey <hi>God</hi> then diſpleaſe great ones; if thou deſireſt peace without any reſpect to truth; if thou doſt allow thy ſelfe in the practice of any knowne groſſe ſinne, if thou takeſt liberty to ſinne becauſe <hi>God</hi> is mercifull, and forbeares to execute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpeedily; if thou doſt not beleeve all things to be ordered by <hi>Gods</hi> providence, and in particular acknowledge him in all thou either receiveſt or ſuffereſt; if thou murmureſt when thou wanteſt any thing, without ever thinking of the many things thou haſt beyond thy deſert; if thou canſt heare <hi>God</hi> blaſphemed and diſhonoured, without being moved thereat; if the ſcandalous lives of Profeſſors, or the multitude of Hereſies that are daily broached make thee thinke, and ſpeake evill of the way of truth; if thou didſt never ſee thy ſelfe out of meaſure ſinfull, as being many waies guilty of the breach of every of the Commandements in particular, and ſo in a loſt condition, utterly deſpayring of all helpe in thy ſelfe, acknowledging that thou haſt deſerved all the plagues of this life, and of that which is to come; if thou art not as well troubled for originall guilt, for ſinnes of omiſſion, for the evill which cleaves to thy beſt workes, and for thy very thoughts, as for thy actuall and manifeſt evill deeds; if thou haſt made vowes, and promiſed amendment when the rod was on thy back, but never cared to performe the ſame when thou wert releaſed; if thou art not induſtrious after the meanes of grace; if thou loveſt not to heare <hi>Chriſts</hi> voyce; if thou findeſt not the Word more quick, and powerfull, and ſweet, and efficatious then any other writings; if it, and the ſpirit going along with it hath not brought thee out of darkneſſe into marvellous light, in compariſon of thy former darkneſſe; if thou art ignorant of the principalls of Religion in the midſt of ſo much light and meanes, and canſt not yeeld a reaſon of the hope that is in thee; if thou doſt not finde a manifeſt change in thy judgement, affections, and actions from what they were by nature; if the old man hath not changed with the new man; worldly wiſedome with heavenly wiſedome, carnall love for ſpirituall love; ſervile feare for chriſtian and filiall feare, idle thoughts for holy thoughts, vaine words for holy and wholſome words, fleſhly workes for workes of righteouſneſſe, &amp;c. as if thou wert caſt into a new mould
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119873:20"/>even hating what thou formerly lovedſt, and loving what thou formerly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedſt; if thou art not aſhamed of thy former converſation; if thou haſt not been often and grievouſly aſſaulted with feares and doubtings, and often in combate between the fleſh and the ſpirit, the ſpirit getting the better; if thou doſt not more feare the want of grace then conſide in what thou haſt; if thou art nor jealous leſt thy heart ſhould deceive thee; yea, if thou art not hated of the world, and evill ſpoken of for well doing, thou art the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills ſervant, and not as yet one of that ſmall number whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath choſen out of the world to beleeve in his name; for theſe, or any one of theſe ſignes ſufficiently brand thee for a wicked man; if you would ſee it proved undeniably from Gods Word, read my <hi>Cure of Miſpriſion,</hi> Sections the 20. and 21.</p>
               <p>§. 68. But leaſt any weake <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſhould thinke himſelfe unſound, and ſo none of <hi>Chriſts,</hi> becauſe he falls ſhort of this deſcription of a true Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and findes wanting in himſelfe, perhaps many of the former ſignes or evidences herein ſet forth; or ſhould be diſcouraged by reaſon of his many and great faylings, together with the weakneſſe of his faith and love, as for the moſt part the true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is as fearefull to entertaine a good opinion of himſelfe, as the falſe is unwilling to be driven from it; let ſuch an one take ſpeciall notice in the firſt place, that there are three ſorts of true and ſound <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>John</hi> makes the diſtinction, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.12, 13. the firſt ſort are <hi>babes</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> viz. ſuch as are new borne, or but weakly qualifyed with the graces of <hi>Gods Spirit;</hi> A ſecond are <hi>ſtrong men,</hi> as having the gifts of the Spirit lively, and in power: The third are <hi>Fathers,</hi> ſuch as have had long experience in the powerfull practice of Chriſtianity, and been long exerciſed in all kinds or well doing. This done:</p>
               <p>§. 69. Secondly let him know, That as <hi>God</hi> requires no other obedience in the beſt then Evangelicall, ſo he lookes not for the ſame meaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of grace from <hi>Babes,</hi> and <hi>ſtrong men,</hi> or from ſtrong men and <hi>Fathers,</hi> for <hi>God</hi> accepteth of every man according to the grace he hath received, be it more or leſte, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. as is manifeſt by that Parable of the <hi>Talents, Matth.</hi> 25.20. to 24. yea, what Father or Maſter will not from his young and newly weaned Child, or ſick and weake ſervant, accept of the will for the deed? and ſhall not <hi>God</hi> much more, who is both the Father of mercies, and the Author of mercy and compaſſion in others? Yes undoubtedly; as let it be granted, that thy knowledge is ſtill ſmall, thy faith weake, thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity cold, thy heart dull and hard, thy good workes few and imperfect, and all thy zealous reſolutions eaſily hindered and quite over-throwne with every ſmall temptation, yet <hi>God</hi> that worketh in us both the will and the worke, will accept the will for the worke; and that which is wanting in us <hi>Chriſt</hi> will ſupply with his owne righteouſneſſe; he reſpecteth not what we can doe ſo much as what we would doe, and that which we would performe and cannot, he eſteemeth it as though it were performed; thus he taketh an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119873:20"/>heart deſirous to repent and beleeve for a penitent and beleeving heart, whereas take away the will and all acts in <hi>Gods</hi> ſight are equall. Well might I doubt of my ſalvation ſayes <hi>Bradford,</hi> feeling the weakneſſe of my faith, love, hope, &amp;c. if theſe were the cauſes of my ſalvation, but there is no other cauſe of it, or of <hi>Gods</hi> mercy, but his mercy. Againe,</p>
               <p>§. 70. Thirdly, you are to obſerve that as Nature ſo Grace riſes by many degrees to perfection, we grow in grace and ſaving knowledge, as a childe does in ſtature and underſtanding, untill we attaine to glory, which is grace perfected; yea, grace in its growth is but like the change of a mans haire from black to grey, or the growth of a <hi>Tree,</hi> which is not accompliſht in a moneth, or a yeare, but in many yeares we not perceiving how.</p>
               <p>§. 71. Fourthly, conſider alſo that the beſt have their failings, as had <hi>Abraham, Jacob, David, Peter,</hi> &amp;c. you have heard of the patience of <hi>Job,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>James,</hi> and have we not heard alſo of his fits of impatiency? Yes, but it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> mercifully to over-looke that; and ſo of <hi>Aſah,</hi> who had divers, and thoſe no ſmall faults, yet with one breath doth <hi>God</hi> report both theſe; the high places were not removed, and nevertheleſſe <hi>Aſahs</hi> heart was perfect; ſo our faylings be not wilfull, though they be many and great, yet they cannot hinder our intereſt in the promiſes of <hi>God;</hi> an honeſt and ſincere heart beares out many errors in the eye of mercy, <hi>God</hi> will not ſee weakneſſes where he ſees truth; yea, if we hate our corruptions, and ſtrive againſt them, they ſhall not be counted ours: It is not I, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> but the ſinne that dwelleth in me, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.20. And indeed were it not ſo, what would become of us? for the worke of grace though it doth not ſuffer <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to live as they liſt, yet it doth not inable them to live as they would; it is not ſo broad as to allow of corruption, nor ſo narrow but it will permit of corruption.</p>
               <p>§. 72. But fifthly, leaſt the former conſiderations ſhould not ſerve, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me ingeniouſly to theſe queſtions:</p>
               <p>Doſt thou not ſinde that the Word and Spirit hath wrought an apparant change in thy judgement, affections, and actions to what they were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? Is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> thy greateſt joy, ſin thy greateſt ſorrow, and grace the prime object of thy deſires? Art thou not carefull in the uſe of the means, to attaine faith in the promiſe of <hi>Gods</hi> mercy made in <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Doſt thou not love <hi>God,</hi> and the people of <hi>God;</hi> yea, art thou not prone to ſpeake in their defence when thou heareſt them reviled, and contemned by wicked and ungodly men? Doſt thou not rejoyce when the righteous are exalted, and grieve when the wicked beare rule? Doſt thou not deſire and pray for the ſalvation of others? Is it not grievous to thee to heare <hi>God</hi> blaſphemed, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured? Doſt thou not make conſcience of ſanctifying his <hi>Sabbaths?</hi> Art thou not as conſcienſcious alone, and in private where <hi>God</hi> onely ſees thee, as if thy greateſt enemy, or all the world did behold thee? Doſt thou not make conſcience of evill thoughts, grieve for thy unprofitableneſſe under the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119873:21"/>meanes of grace, for the evill which cleaves to thy beſt actions, and for ſins of omiſion? When thou doſt any thing amiſſe doſt thou not accuſe thy ſelfe? if any thing well, doſt thou not give all the praiſe to God? Whatever thou injoyeſt on this ſide Hell, doſt thou not thinke thy ſelfe unworthy of it? Doſt thou not more feare the want of grace then confide in what thou haſt? Art thou not evill ſpoken of for well doing? Doſt thou not love zeale and devotion in others? Thou art not of a reprobate judgement, touching things, actions, and perſons, accounting good evill, and evill good; nor doſt thou think the worſe of a man for having of a tender conſcience: Thou art not ſo offended when offences come as to thinke the worſe of the way of truth, yea, when ſtrange things happen doſt thou not make an wholſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction thereof? If ſo, my ſoule for thine thou art a true Beleever, and not an hypocrite whatever thy failings be; yea, if thou ſhouldeſt finde but a few of theſe ſignes in thy ſelfe thou needeſt not much feare thine eſtate, for a few Grapes will ſhew that the plant is a Vine, and not a Thorne; yea, where there is any one grace in truth there is every one in their meaſure: if thou art ſure thou haſt love, I am ſure thou haſt faith; for they are as inſeparable as fire and heat, life and motion; and ſo of other graces,</p>
               <p>§. 73. But ſixthly, for I will goe yet further with thee; ſuppoſe nothing that I have hitherto ſaid will ſatisfie thee, and that thou wilt not auknowledge any of theſe graces to be in thee, yet ſtill thy caſe may be good enough; for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in times of ſpirituall diſtemper and deſerſion is as one in a ſound, in which caſe the ſoule doth not exerciſe her functions; he neither heares, nor ſees, nor feeles, yet ſhe is ſtill in the body: <hi>Chriſt</hi> is as the <hi>Sunne</hi> to our ſoules, and we are like <hi>Elementary bodies;</hi> which lighten and darken, coole and warme, dye and revive; as the Sun preſents or abſents it ſelfe from them. Whence it comes to paſſe that we have ſo much crying out in horrour of conſcience, I am damned, I am damned; yea, it is a wonder to ſee how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny truly humbled ſinners, who have ſo tender conſciences that they dare not yeeld to the leaſt evill for the worlds goods, and refuſe no meanes of being made better; turne every probation into reprobation, every dejection into rejection; and if they be caſt downe they cry out, they are caſt away; but in ſuch diſtempers a man is not a competent Judge in his owne caſe, as in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Lawes there is anullity held of words and actions extorted, and wrong from men by feare; becauſe in ſuch caſes a man is held not to have power, or command in ſome ſort of himſelfe. A troubled ſoule is like troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we can diſcerne nothing cleerly in it; wherefore in ſuch caſes a man muſt call to remembrance the times paſt, and how it hath been with him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.2. to 12. and likewiſe <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 31. And his muſt thou doe, and then if ever thou hadſt true faith wrought in thy heart it can never be cleane extinguiſhed; and ſo of love and godly ſorrow, for the gifts and calling of <hi>God</hi> are without repentance; as it is <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. I the Lord change not, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3, 6. And the weakeſt faith if true, though it be not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119873:21"/>the like ſtrong, yet it is the like precious faith to that of <hi>Abrahams,</hi> whereby to lay hold, and put on the perfect righteouſneſſe of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> yea, the truth of grace, be the meaſure never ſo ſmall is alwaies bleſt with perſeverance; and if grace but conquer us firſt, we by it ſhall conquer all things elſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be corruptions within us, or temptations without us; yea, to ſpeake rightly, thou art the better to be thought of, and the leſſe to be feared for this thy feare, for no man ſo truly loves as he that feares to offend; and good is that feare which keepes us from evill acts, yea, as a bleeding wound is better then that which bleeds not; ſo thy very complaint of ſinne ſpringing from a diſpleaſure againſt it ſhewes, that there is ſomething in thee oppoſite to ſinne, viz. that thou art penitent in affection though not in action; even as a Childe is rationall in power, though not in act; neither was the <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> ever ſo worthy as when he thought himſelfe moſt unworthy; for all our worthineſſe is in a capable miſery.</p>
               <p>§. 74. But here by the way obſerve one caution, as the <hi>Playſter</hi> muſt not be leſſe then the <hi>ſore,</hi> ſo the <hi>tem</hi> muſt not be bigger then the <hi>wound.</hi> Though the grievouſneſſe of our ſins ſhould increaſe our repentance, yet they ſhould not diminiſh our faith, and aſſurance of pardon and forgiveneſſe. Becauſe the <hi>Law</hi> is not more a <hi>Glaſſe</hi> to ſhew us our ſins, then the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is a <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> to waſh them away; wherefore caſt not both thine eyes upon thy ſinne, but reſerve one to behold the remedy; looke upon the Law to keepe thee from <hi>preſumption,</hi> and upon the Goſpell to keepe thee from <hi>deſpaire;</hi> this is both a ſweet and an even courſe. But as an empty <hi>Veſſell</hi> cloſe luted, though you throw it into the midſt of the <hi>Sea</hi> will receive no water, ſo all pleas are in vaine to them that are deafned with their owne feares; for as <hi>Mary</hi> would not be comforted with the ſight and ſpeech of <hi>Angels,</hi> no not with the fight and ſpeech of <hi>Jeſus</hi> himſelfe, till he made her know that it was <hi>Jeſus;</hi> ſo untill the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> ſprinkleth the conſcience with the blond of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſheds his love into the heart; nothing will doe, no Creature can take off wrath from the conſcience but he that ſet it on; wherefore the <hi>God</hi> of peace give you the peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding, yea, O Lord, ſpeake thou <hi>muſick</hi> to the wounded conſcience, <hi>thunder</hi> to the ſeared; that thy Juſtice may reclaime the one, thy mercy releeve the other, and thy favour comfort us all, with peace and ſalvation in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 75. The comfort of what hath been ſaid in theſe ſeven laſt Sections, is intended and belongs to weake <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> troubled conſciences, and thoſe that would faine doe better; but let no unbeleever, impenitent, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon meddle with it, for all ſuch are to know that their very beſt ſervices, as praying, and faſting, and receiving, and giving of Almes, &amp;c. (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not done in faith, and obedience to the Word, and that <hi>God</hi> may be glorified thereby) are no better in <hi>Gods</hi> account then if they had ſtaine a <hi>Man,</hi> or cut of a <hi>Doggs neck,</hi> or offered <hi>Swines blood,</hi> or bleſſed an <hi>Idoll,</hi> as himſelfe affirmes, <hi>Iſay</hi> 66.3. Nor will <hi>God</hi> accept of any action un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119873:22"/>it flowes from a pious and good heart ſanctified by the Holy Ghoſt; yea civill honeſty ſevered from true piety, humility, ſaving knowledge, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere love to <hi>God,</hi> true obedience to his Word, juſtifying faith, a zeale of <hi>Gods</hi> glory, and a deſire to edifie and win others, <hi>God</hi> will neither accept nor reward, but account of their morall vertues as of ſhining or gliſtering ſinnes; becauſe they ſpring from pride, ignorance, infidelity, ſelfe-love, and other ſuch carnall reſpects, as many examples prove, namely, <hi>Caines</hi> ſacrifycing, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.12. the <hi>Iewes</hi> faſting, <hi>Iſay</hi> 58. thoſe reprobates preaching in <hi>Chriſts</hi> name, and caſting out Devills, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22, 23. and the like, whoſe outward workes were the ſame which the godly performe; and what ſaith <hi>Auſtine</hi> moſt excellently, There is no true vertue where there is no true Religion; and that conſcience which is not directed by the Word even when it does beſt does ill, becauſe it doth it not in faith, obedience, and love.</p>
               <p>§. 76. Secondly let them know, that being out of <hi>Chriſt</hi> they are bound to keepe the whole Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2, 3. or ſtand liable to ſuffer the penalty thereof for not keeping it; for though this be the condition of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Beleeve and thou ſhalt be ſaved;</hi> yet all that they have to truſt unto is, <hi>Doe this and live, Rom.</hi> 10.5. and curſed is every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the Book of the Law to doe them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. And I wiſh that they would ſeriouſly thinke of it, and what need they have of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whom they rather perſecute then obey his Goſpell in love.</p>
               <p>§. 77. Indeed let them get a true lively and juſtifying faith, put ye off concerning the former converſation, the <hi>old man</hi> which is corrupted through the deceiveable luſts, and be renued in the ſpirit of your mindes; and put on the <hi>new man,</hi> which after <hi>God</hi> is created in righteouſneſſe and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. and then <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and all his <hi>benefits</hi> and <hi>promiſes</hi> will belong unto you, but not before; in the meane time you are in your bloud, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 16.6. and have to anſwer not onely for your originall guilt, but for every thought, word, and action of yours from your infancy, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.12, 13. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.53. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. to 7. enough to ſtartle you if you be not ſtarke dead.</p>
               <p>§. 78. But perhaps thy heart and conſcience is not onely Sermon, but Thunder proofe, and then nothing will doe good upon thee (the caſe of all incorrigible ones) yea moſt men now adaies are judgement proofe; and let them be never ſo cleerly convinc'd from the word that they are in a dangerous condition, all thoughts thereof preſently paſſe away like the ſound of a Bell that is rung; or if not, Satan can furniſh them with an evaſion, be the caſe what it will; amongſt many of his deluſions I will mention two of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, and which I hold to be the ſtrongeſt barres to keepe men out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that can be named.</p>
               <p>The firſt is this, Never regard (will he ſay to a poore ſoule) what a few melancholly Preciſſions ſay when every one doth ſo, and ſo; or every one is of this or that judgement; yea, doe not ſuch and ſuch the like, who are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119873:22"/>wiſer, and greater, and better men then your ſelfe? They are of another minde, neither doe they trouble themſelves ſo much about Religion, and yet they looke to ſpeed as well as the preciſeſt; yea will he ſay, Doe ye not ſee many <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and great <hi>Profeſſors of Religion,</hi> who pretend it is good being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and holy, and preſſe others to it, that doe onely pretend it, for they live as looſely, and deale as unjuſtly as any other men; and they are not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of what they doe, and this you may be ſure of, that if they did ſpeake as they thinke they would doe as they ſpeake; therefore what ſhould ye be ſo ſingular, will ye be wiſer then all your friends, or neighbours; yea, then nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and nine parts of the Kingdome? What a mad conceit were this? then yeelds the poore ſoule, and counts it a pleaſure too that he is ſeduced, and by this kinde of Sophiſtry Satan prevailes with millions; yea, I have ever noted, that this one artleſſe perſwaſion of others doe ſo, prevailes more with the world then all the places of reaſon, but this plea or argument is not more common and taking then it is ſortſh and dangerous, if it be well lookt into; for beſides that it is <hi>Gods</hi> expreſſe charge, <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to doe evill, Exod.</hi> 23.2. and Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> everlaſting rule, <hi>Faſhion not your ſelves like unto this world, Rom.</hi> 12.2. Our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath plainely told us, <hi>That the greateſt number goe the broad way to deſtruction,</hi> and <hi>but a few the narrow way which leadeth unto life, Matth.</hi> 7.13, 14. And Saint <hi>John, That the number of thoſe whom Satan ſhall deceive is as the ſand of the ſea,</hi> Revel. 20.8. and 13.16. Iſay 10.22. Rom. 9.27. yea, that <hi>the whole world lyeth in wickedneſſe,</hi> 1 John 5.19. whereas thoſe whom <hi>Chriſt hath choſen</hi> out of it, and <hi>that beleeve the Goſpell,</hi> are but a <hi>little flocke,</hi> and <hi>few in number,</hi> Luke 12.32. Revel. 3.4. Iſay 53.1. Rom. 10.16. 2 Cor. 4.4. which teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies have proved true in all former Ages; there could not be found eight righteous perſons in the <hi>old world,</hi> for one was an impious <hi>Cham,</hi> all <hi>Sodome</hi> afforded not ten; <hi>Eliah</hi> could ſay, <hi>I onely remaine a Prophet of the Lord, but Baals prophets are four hundred and fifty,</hi> 1 Kings 18.22. And <hi>Micha</hi> complaines of the multitude of the wicked in his time, and ſmall number of the faithfull, <hi>Micha</hi> 7.2. <hi>Behold</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſaiah, I and the Children whom the Lord hath given me, are for ſignes and wonders in Iſrael, Iſay</hi> 8.18. ſo few and rare that they were gazed upon as monſters. And what faith the Lord himſelfe; <hi>Though the number of the Children of Iſrael be as the ſand of the ſea, yet but a remnant ſhall be ſaved, Iſay</hi> 10.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.27. Neither hath it been otherwiſe ſince the Goſpell, <hi>the whole City</hi> went out to ſend <hi>Chriſt</hi> packing, not a <hi>Gadaren</hi> was found that either dehorted his fellow, or oppoſed the motion, <hi>Mat</hi> 8.34. When <hi>Pilate</hi> asked, What ſhall be done with <hi>Jeſus,</hi> all with one conſent cryed out, <hi>Let him be Crucified,</hi> Matth. 27.22. there was a generall ſhout for <hi>Diana</hi> for two houres together, <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians;</hi> not one man tooke <hi>Pauls</hi> part, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.34. yea the <hi>Jewes</hi> told <hi>Paul,</hi> that his <hi>Sect</hi> was <hi>every where ſpoken againſt,</hi> Acts 28, 22. yea <hi>all, both ſmall and great, rich and poore, free and bond receive the marke of the Beaſt in their fore-heads,</hi> Rev. 13.16
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119873:23"/>ſo that number is but an ill ſigne of a good cauſe; or rather it is the beſt note of the worſt way.</p>
               <p>§. 79. Secondly, nor will any wiſe man thinke his actions ever the more warrantable for that he does as the greateſt, richeſt, and nobleſt of the Land doe; for <hi>Not many noble are called:</hi> but (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>God hath choſen the baſe things of the world, and things that are deſpiſed to confound the mighty,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.26, 27. <hi>And hath choſen the poore of this world to be rich in faith,</hi> James 2.5. yea, <hi>he filleth the hungry with good things,</hi> whereas <hi>he ſendeth away the rich empty,</hi> Luke 1.52, 53. Neither is this the manner of his donation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but of his acceptation alſo, for <hi>God</hi> eſteemes more of vertue clad in raggs then of vice in velvit; he reſpects a man not for his greatneſſe, but for his goodneſſe; not for his birth, but for his New Birth; not for his honour, but for his holineſſe; not for his wealth, but for his wiſedome: <hi>The righteous ſaith</hi> Solomon <hi>is more worthy then his neighbour,</hi> Prov. 12.26. and, <hi>Better is the poore that walketh uprightly, then he that perverteth his waies though he be rich,</hi> Prov, 28.6. and thus the <hi>Bareans</hi> are reputed by the Holy Ghoſt; <hi>More noble men then they of Theſſalonica, becauſe they received the Word with all readineſſe, and ſearched the Scriptures whether thoſe things were ſo which</hi> Paul <hi>preached,</hi> Act. 17.11. Whence it is that <hi>David</hi> thought it not ſo happy for him to be a <hi>King</hi> in his owne houſe as <hi>a Doore keeper in Gobs houſe.</hi> That godly <hi>Conſtantine</hi> rejoyced more in being the ſervant of <hi>Chriſt</hi> then in being <hi>Emperour</hi> of the whole world; that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour preferred the title of <hi>Membrum Eccleſia</hi> before that of <hi>Caput imperii,</hi> profeſſing that he had rather be a Saint and no <hi>King,</hi> then a <hi>King</hi> and no Saint; yea <hi>Ignaſius</hi> ſaid, he had rather be a Martyr then a <hi>Monarch.</hi> Beſides, experience proves great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nobility, and riches, to be a moſt deceitfull rule to walke by; for, <hi>the Kings of the earth band themſelves, and the Princes are aſſembled together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt,</hi> Pſal. 2.2. And in the firſt of <hi>Kings,</hi> 20.16. we read of no leſſe then two and thirty <hi>Kings</hi> in a cluſter that were every one drunke; and elſewhere, that a thouſand of the chiefe <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> committed fornication, and were all deſtroyed for their labour in one day, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. yea of twenty <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Judah</hi> which the Scripture mentions, we read of but ſix that were godly, and of eighteene <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> all but two are branded by the Holy Ghoſt for wicked, and yet this Nation was <hi>Gods</hi> peculier and choſen people out of all the world; and laſtly, when the <hi>Rulers</hi> ſate in counſell againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> none ſpake for him but <hi>Nichodemas,</hi> Joh, 7.50, 51. All which ſhewes; that it is neither a good nor a ſafe way to imitate other mens examples, be they never ſo rich, never ſo great; or if we ſinne together, we ſhall be ſure to periſh together; as when thoſe <hi>three and twenty thouſand Iſraelites committed fornication</hi> after the example of the chiefe <hi>Princes,</hi> they were every one deſtroyed, both leaders and followers, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. and as when thoſe other <hi>Cities</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Sodoms</hi> luſt, they were all conſumed with <hi>Sodoms</hi> fire, <hi>Judg.</hi> 7.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119873:23"/>
               <p>§. 80. But thirdly admit thou couldeſt alleadge for thine excuſe, that thou doſt but as moſt of the wiſe, learned, and greateſt Schollers in the Land doe, yet all were one, this could not excuſe thee; for firſt, <hi>Not many wiſe men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh are called, but God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wiſe,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.26, 27, 29. yea, <hi>the preaching of Chriſt crucified, was fooliſhneſſe to the wiſe Sages</hi> of the world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. It pleaſeth <hi>God</hi> for the moſt part, to <hi>hide the myſteries of ſalvation from the wiſe and learned, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed them unto babes,</hi> Matth. 11.25. Luke 10.21. yea the ſaving knowledge of <hi>Chriſt is hid to all that are loſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.3. but if once men abuſe their knowledge and learning to <hi>Gods</hi> diſhonour, and comply with Satan and the world againſt the Church (as how many Schollars in all ages of the world have reſembled <hi>Trajan,</hi> who was indued with great knowledge and other ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular vertues, but deſaced them all by hating Chriſtianity, and oppoſing the power of godlineſſe) in this caſe he taketh that knowledge which once they had from them, as he tooke heat from the fire when it would burne his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.27. <hi>I will deſtroy the tokens of the Sooth-ſayers,</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and make them that conjecture fooles; I will turne the wiſe men backward, and make their knowledge fooliſhneſſe,</hi> Iſay 44.25. And againe, <hi>He taketh the wiſe in their owne craftineſſe, and the councell of the wicked is made fooliſh,</hi> Job 5.13. And juſtly are they forſaken of their reaſon who have abandoned <hi>God;</hi> yea moſt juſt it is, that they who want grace ſhould want wit too, for which read, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. Thus I might goe on and ſhew, that we may not imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the actions, nor follow the examples of the beſt and holieſt men in every thing they doe, though we have ſome plauſible reaſons for our doing ſo, and alſo good and holy intentions in our ſo doing, or if we doe that, we may goe to Hell notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>§. 81. But you will ſay, if neither cuſtome of the greateſt number, nor of the greateſt men, nor of the greateſt Schollers, nor of the beſt and holieſt men, though we have reaſon for our doing it, and good intentions in the doing of it is a ſufficient warrant for our actions, but that all theſe are croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and deceitfull guides; then what may be a ſafe guide, and an infallible rule in all caſes to ſteere by and ſquare all our actions?</p>
               <p>I anſwer; As a <hi>rule</hi> directeth the Artificer in his worke, and keepeth him from erring, ſo doth <hi>Gods Word</hi> direct the religious in their lives, and keepe them from erring. The right way is the ſignified Will of <hi>God,</hi> and whatſoever ſwerves from, or is repugnant to the right is wrong and crooked; Law and Precept is a ſtraight line to ſhew us whether we doe miſ-beleeve, or miſ-live, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>John</hi> 5.39. And it hath ever been the care of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to ſtick cloſe to the written Word, having alwaies, and in all caſes an eye thereunto; and without this written Word, a man in the world is as a <hi>Ship</hi> on the <hi>Sea</hi> without a guide; yea, he that lives without making this his rule, he who ſets not the <hi>Diall</hi> or <hi>Clock</hi> of his life by this <hi>Sunne,</hi> he who directeth not his courſe in walking by this <hi>North-pole,</hi> or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119873:24"/>
                  <hi>Load-ſtarre,</hi> but by the wavouring, uncertaine, and moveable <hi>ſtarres</hi> of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, example, reaſon, and good intentions, ſayles without a <hi>Compaſſe;</hi> and may looke every minute to be ſwallowed up in the <hi>Ocia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of ſinne and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor will any that have grace in their hearts make cuſtome, example, or the badneſſe of the times a cloake to excuſe their conformity in evill courſes, but rather a ſpurre to incite them to be ſo much the more carefull not to be ſwayed with the common ſtreame; and happy is that man who makes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vices ſteps to climbe to <hi>Heaven</hi> by, as it fared with righteous <hi>Lot;</hi> and ſo doth every wiſe and good man, as why ſhould they not make this uſe of the corruptions of the times, when even the mud of the world by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious <hi>Hollander</hi> is turned to an uſefull fuell. If the <hi>Ayre</hi> be generally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious, had we not need to be ſo much the more ſtrict in our Diet, and carefull in the uſe of wholſome preſervatives? Nor is fingularity in ſuch caſes onely lawfull but laudable, when vice growes into faſhion, ſingularity is a vertue; and when ſanctity is counted ſingularity, happy is he that goeth alone, and reſolves to be an example to others; yea, moſt happy is he that can ſtand upright when the world declines, and can indeavour to repaire the common ruine with a conſtancy in goodneſſe; that can reſolve with <hi>Joſhua, whatever the world doth, yet, I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord,</hi> Joſh. 24.15. It was <hi>Noahs</hi> happineſſe in the <hi>old world,</hi> that he followed not the worlds faſhions; he beleeved alone when all the world conteſted againſt him, and he was ſaved alone when all the world periſhed without him. It was <hi>Lots</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, that he ſollowed not the faſhions of <hi>Sodome.</hi> It was <hi>Abrahams</hi> happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that he did not like the <hi>Chaldreans; Daniels</hi> happineſſe, that he did not like the <hi>Babilonians.</hi> It was good for <hi>Job</hi> that he was ſingular in the Land of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zze;</hi> good for <hi>Nichodemas,</hi> that he was ſingular among the <hi>Rulers,</hi> as now they all finde to their great comfort, and exceeding great reward; yea, it was happy for <hi>Ruben,</hi> that he was oppoſite to all his <hi>Brethren;</hi> happy for <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leb,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> that they were oppoſite to the reſt of the <hi>Spies,</hi> happy for the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that <hi>their cuſtomes were divers, and contrary to all other people,</hi> though <hi>Haman</hi> was pleaſed to make it their great and hainous crime, <hi>Eſter</hi> 3.8. Happy for <hi>Luther,</hi> that he was oppoſite to the reſt of his Country: and no leſſe happy ſhall we be, if with the <hi>Deere</hi> we can feed againſt the wind of popular applauſe; if with the <hi>Sturgion,</hi> or <hi>Crab-fiſh,</hi> we can ſwimme againſt the ſtreame of cuſtome and example; if with <hi>Atticus,</hi> we can cleave to the right though loſing ſide; or if we doe nor, we ſhall miſſe of the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way, and conſequently faile of entring in at the ſtraite Gate, for the greateſt part ſhuts out <hi>God</hi> upon <hi>Earth,</hi> and is excluded from <hi>God</hi> elſewhere; <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.13, 14. And indeed, if <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his twelve <hi>Apoſtles</hi> be on our ſide, what need we care though <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> and all the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> and the whole Nation of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> together with a world of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faction be againſt us; and certainely if thou wert not a ſoole, thou wouldeſt hold it better to be in the ſmall number of <hi>Chriſts little flock</hi> which are to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119873:24"/>ſaved, then in the numerous heards of thoſe <hi>Goates</hi> that are deſtinated to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: and ſo much for anſwer to Satans firſt plea or objection. But,</p>
               <p>§. 82. Secondly, he hath a worſe and more dangerous deluſion then this, for if he ſee a man convinc'd that he is nothing ſo as he ought to be, (that he may keepe him ſtill impenitent) he will ſay unto him, Trouble not thy ſelfe with theſe things, doſt thou not know that <hi>God</hi> is mercifull, and that <hi>Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners,</hi> witneſſe the <hi>Thiefe</hi> upon the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> who was heard, and ſaved by him at the very laſt houre; and upon this ground a world of men in a carnall preſumption goe on to deſtruction, without ever bethinking themſelves; for ſay they, Let the worſt that can come, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? at the laſt houre, and ſaying, <hi>Lord have mercy upon me</hi> will make all even, otherwiſe <hi>God</hi> is not ſo good as his word; who ſaith, At what time ſoever a ſinner repenteth, &amp;c. but let the argument be well ſcand, and this will be found as ſottiſh, deceitfull, and dangerous as the other; wherefore that Satan (who is alwaies a liar) may not by his cunning deluſions gull you of your ſoules, and plunge you into everlaſting horrour; conſider with me in the firſt place, that as <hi>God</hi> is mercifull, ſo he is alſo juſt, and true, and ſpeakes as he meanes in his Word; yea, he is truth it ſelfe, and his Word is the ground and touchſtone of all truth; wherefore, <hi>if any ſpirit, or an Angell from Heaven croſſe the written Word, we are to hold him accurſed,</hi> Gal. 1.8, 9. Now we ſhall finde, that ſalvation is not more promiſed to the godly (in any part of the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Old Teſtament</hi> or <hi>New</hi>) then eternall death and deſtruction is threatned to the wicked, as you may ſee, <hi>John</hi> 5.28. to 47. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.29. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.24. &amp; 29.19, 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.8. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Jer</hi> 16.13. <hi>Mattth.</hi> 7.13, 14. &amp; 25.34.41. <hi>James</hi> 2.13. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.6. <hi>Luke.</hi> 13.24. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18. yea, <hi>God</hi> hath ſufficiently manifeſted his juſtice and ſeverity already in puniſhing ſinne, and powring vengeance upon thoſe that have provoked him, as upon the <hi>Angels,</hi> our <hi>firſt Parents,</hi> and all the race of Man-kinde; upon the <hi>old world,</hi> upon whole <hi>Monarchs</hi> and <hi>Empires,</hi> upon whole <hi>Nations, Cities.</hi> and <hi>Fomilies,</hi> upon divers <hi>perticular perſons,</hi> as upon <hi>Pharaoh, Nadah,</hi> and <hi>Abihu, Chora, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> with their 250. <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> and many thouſand of the <hi>Children of Iſrael,</hi> upon <hi>Hammon</hi> and <hi>Balaam, Saul</hi> and <hi>Doeg, Abſalon</hi> and <hi>Achittophel, Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezabell, Senacharib</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> the two <hi>Captaines and their fifties, Herod</hi> and <hi>Judas, Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> with a world of others; yea, how ſeverely hath he dealt with his owne children when they finned againſt him? viz. with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Ely,</hi> who were in ſingular favour with him; yea with <hi>David, a man after Gods owne heart,</hi> and that after his ſinne was remitted, and laſtly with his owne Sonne, that no finne might goe unpuniſhed, which may make all impenitent perſons tremble; for if <hi>God</hi> was ſo juſt and ſevere to his owne Sonne, that nothing would appeaſe him but his death on the Croſſe, how can the wicked his enemies looke to be ſpared? and if <hi>Gods</hi> owne Servants, who are as deare and neare to him as <hi>the apple of his own eye,</hi> or as the <hi>ſignet on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119873:25"/>his right hand,</hi> ſuffer ſo many and grievous afflictions here, what ſhall his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſuffer in Hell? But becauſe thou ſhalt have nothing to object, Wilt thou beleeve <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, whom thou thinkeſt came to ſave all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently; if thou wilt turne but to <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. and he will tell thee, that at his comming to Judgement he will as well ſay to the diſobedient, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, which is prepared for the Devill and his Angels;</hi> as to the obedient, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, prepared for you from the foundation of the world, ver.</hi> 34.41. Againe, leaſt any ſhould be over conſident, he tells all men plainly, that <hi>the gate of heaven is ſo ſtraight that few ſhall finde it,</hi> Matth. 7.13, 14. and that <hi>many ſhall ſeeke to enter thereat and ſhall not be able,</hi> Luke 13.24. And that <hi>many are called,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> by the outward miniſtry of the Word) <hi>but few choſen,</hi> Matth. 20.16. &amp; 22.14. ſad predictions for ſuch as apply <hi>Chriſts</hi> Paſſion as a warrant for their liſentiouſneſſe, not as a remedy; and take his Death as a licenſe to ſinne, his Croſſe as a Letters Patent to doe miſchiefe. O that men would ſeriouſly thinke upon theſe Scriptures, together with that, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9. where the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Lord Jeſus ſhall come</hi> the ſecond time <hi>in flaming fire, to render vengeance unto them that know him not, and that obey not his Goſpell,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18. where the Holy Ghoſt tells us, that even the <hi>righteous ſhall ſcarcely be ſaved.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. to 29. where <hi>God</hi> tells us expreſly, that he <hi>will not be mercifull unto ſuch,</hi> as flatter themſelves in an evill way; <hi>but</hi> that <hi>his wrath and ſealouſie ſhall ſmoke againſt them, &amp;c. and that if we will not regard nor hearken unto him when he calls upon us for repentance, he will not heare nor regard us, when in our diſtreſſe and anguiſh we ſhall call upon him for mercy, but even laugh at our deſtruction, and mock when our feare cometh</hi> Prov. 1.24. to 33. and that <hi>he will recompence every man according to his workes be they good or evill,</hi> Revel. 20.13. &amp; 22.12. Rom, 2.6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.4.8.9. &amp; 9.10. &amp;. 11.21. &amp; 16.43. but this is the miſery, and a juſt plague upon our ſo much formality and prophaneſſe, under our ſo much meanes of grace; there be very few men that make not the whole <hi>Bible,</hi> and all the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> they heare, yea the <hi>checks of their owne conſciences,</hi> and the <hi>motions of Gods Spirit</hi> utterly ineffectuall for want of wit and grace to apply the ſame to themſelves; but to goe on.</p>
               <p>§. 83 Secondly, we ſhall finde that though <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Gospel</hi> hath made many large and precious promiſes, yet there are none ſo generall which are not limited with the condition of ſaith, and the fruit thereof unfained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and each of them are ſo tyed and entayled that none can lay claime to them but true Beleevers which repent, <hi>and turne from all their ſinnes to ſerve him in holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> Heb. 12.14. &amp; 5.9. Marke 16.16. John 3.36. Iſay 59.20. Neither was it ever heard that any aſcended into <hi>Heaven</hi> without going up the ſtayers of obedience and good workes, that any have attained unto everlaſting life without faith, repentance, and ſanctification, for even the <hi>Thiefe upon the Croſſe</hi> (whom
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119873:25"/>you ignorantly alleadge) beleeved in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſhewed the fruites of his faith in acknowledging his owne ſinne, reproving his fellow, and confeſſing our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> even then when his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> denied and forſooke him, in calling upon his name, deſiring, and confidently truſting by his meanes and merits to have everlaſting life. And indeed, the very end of <hi>Gods</hi> electing, and of <hi>Chriſts</hi> redeeming us was; <hi>That we might be holy,</hi> Eph. 1.4. Mat. 19.17 and therefore he bindes it with an oath, <hi>That whomſoever he redeemeth out of the hands of their ſpirituall enemies, they ſhall worſhip him in holineſſe and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe all the dayes of their lives,</hi> Luke 1.70. to 76. 1 Pet. 2.24. they therefore that never came to be holy were never choſen, never redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; other Scriptures to this purpoſe are many, ſee onely <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.17. nor ought any indeed to <hi>call upon Chriſt,</hi> or once to name him with their mouthes, except they <hi>depart from iniquity,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.19 Neither doth the <hi>Thiefes</hi> example make any whit for the comfort of procra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinators; for Firſt, we read not that ever he was outwardly called untill this very houre; Secondly, though there was one ſaved at the laſt houre that none might diſpaire, yet there was but one that none ſhould preſume; and millions who had leſſe iniquity have found leſſe mercy. Thirdly, the <hi>Thiefes</hi> converſion was one of the Miracles, with the glory whereof our Saviour would honour the ignominy of his Croſſe, Againe, Fourthly, the Thiefe was ſaved at the very inſtant of time, when our Saviour triumphed on the Croſſe, tooke his leave of the world, and entred into his glory. Now it is uſuall with Princes to ſave ſome hainous Malefactors at their Coronation, when they enter upon their Kingdomes in triumph, which they are never knowne to doe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, which circumſtances being rightly conſidered, together with the wonderfull change ſo ſuddenly wrought in him as I ſhewed before, his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will yeeld little encouragement to men of thy condition; nor was his ſuddaine converſion ever intended in <hi>Gods</hi> purpoſe for a temptation, and yet by Satans policy working upon wicked mens depraved judgements, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt hearts in wreſting this Scripture, it hath proved (by accident) the loſſe of many thouſand ſoules, and take heed it prove not thy caſe; to which end let not Satan any longer bewitch you, ſo to thinke upon Gods mercy as in the meane time to forget that he is alſo juſt, and true; and ſo much for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to thoſe two objections, which Satan findes more prevalent then all the reſt he is able to invent.</p>
               <p>§. 84. Now to winde up all with a word of exhortation, if thou beeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinſt, and reſolveſt upon a new courſe, let thy reſolution be peremptory and conſtant, and take heed thou harden not againe, as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> the <hi>young man</hi> in the Goſpell, <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> did. Reſemble not the <hi>Iron,</hi> which is no longer ſoft then it is in the <hi>fire;</hi> be not like thoſe that are Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, who are much troubled while they are on Shipboard, but preſently well againe when they are come to ſhore; for that good (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) will doe us no good which is not made good by perſeverance. If with theſe premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119873:26"/>the Spirit ſhall vouchſafe to ſtir up in thine heart, any good motions and holy purpoſes to obey <hi>God,</hi> in letting thy ſins goe, <hi>quench not,</hi> grieve not <hi>the Spirit,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.19. <hi>returne not with the Dogge to thy vomit,</hi> leaſt <hi>thy latter end prove ſeven fold worſe then thy beginning,</hi> Matth. 12.43.45. As it fared with <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, and <hi>Judas</hi> the traytor. O it is a fearefull thing <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the grace of God in vaine;</hi> and a deſperate thing being warned of a <hi>Rock,</hi> wilfully to caſt our ſelves upon it! Neither let Satan perſwade you to deferre your repentance, no not an houre, leaſt your reſolution proves as a falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception which never comes to bearing; for as ill Debtors put off their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors firſt one weeke, then another, till at laſt they are able to pay nothing, ſo deale delayers with <hi>God.</hi> Beſides, death may be ſuddaine, even the leaſt of a thouſand things can kill thee, and give thee no leaſure to be ſick.</p>
               <p>§. 85. Secondly, or if death be not ſuddaine, repentance is no ſuch eaſie worke as to be put off to ſickneſſe; and though true repentance be never too late, yet late repentance is ſeldome true; and indeed there is ſmall hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance at the houre of death, where there was no regard of honeſty in the time of life; and Millions are now in Hell who thought they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent hereafter; not being wiſe enough to conſider that it is with ſinne in the heart, as with a tree planted in the ground, which the longer it groweth the harder it is to be pluckt up; or a nayle in a poſt, which is made faſter by every ſtroke of the Hammer. As what ſaith the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Can the Blacke Moore change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots? then may ye alſo doe good that are accuſtomed to doe evill,</hi> Jer. 13.23.</p>
               <p>§. 86. Thirdly, or ſuppoſe after many yeares ſpent in the ſervice of ſinne and Satan thou art willing to relinquiſh thy luſts, and offer to <hi>God</hi> thy ſervice and beſt devotions at the laſt gaſpe, will he accept of them? No, he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly told us the contrary, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24. to 32. yea, is it likely that <hi>God</hi> will accept of thy dry bones when Satan hath ſuckt out all the marrow? That he will give his heavenly and ſpirituall graces at the houre of death, to thoſe who have contemned them all their life? Yea, is it not moſt juſt and equall if <hi>God</hi> will not be found of thoſe that were content to looſe him? If he ſhut his eare againſt their prayers calling to him for pardon, that ſtopt their eares againſt his Voyce calling upon them for repentance. The Lord hath made a promiſe to late repentance, not of late repentance; if thou converteſt to morrow thou art ſure of grace, but thou art not ſure of to morrowes converſion; if in any reaſonable time we pray he will heare us, if we repent he will pardon us, if we amend our lives he will ſave us; but for want of this timely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration <hi>Dives</hi> prayed but was not heard, <hi>Eſau</hi> wept but was not pittied, the <hi>fooliſh Virgins</hi> knockt but were denied, and ſo thouſands have cried unto <hi>God</hi> at the houre of death and found no repentance, but they dyed as they lived, and went from diſpaire unto deſtruction. Wherefore, as you tender the good of your owne ſoule, ſet upon the work preſently, provide with <hi>Joſeph</hi> for the dearth to come; and with <hi>Noah,</hi> in the dayes of thine health build the <hi>Arke</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119873:26"/>of a good Conſcience againſt the flouds of ſickneſſe; imitate the <hi>Ant,</hi> who provides her meat in Summer for the Winter following: yea, doe it while the yerning bowels, the bleeding wounds, and compaſſionute arms of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> lyes open to receive you; whiles ye have health, and life, and meanes, and time to repent; and make your peace with <hi>God.</hi> As you tender I ſay the everlaſting happineſſe and welfare of your almoſt loſt and drowned ſoule, as you expect or hope for grace or mercy, for joy and comfort, for <hi>Heaven</hi> and ſalvation, for endleſſe bliſſe and glory at the laſt; as you would eſcape the direfull Wrath of <hi>God,</hi> the bitter Sentence and Docme of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the never dying ſting and worme of Conſcience, the tormenting and ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcorching flames of Hell, and everlaſting ſeparation from <hi>Gods</hi> blisfull preſence, abjure, and utterly renounce all wilfull and affected evill. To which end;</p>
               <p>§. 87. In the next place be diligent to heare Gods Word (powerfully preached) which is the ſword of the Spirit, that killeth our corruptions, and that unreſiſtable Cannon-ſhot which beateth and battereth downe all the ſtrong holds of ſinne and Satan.</p>
               <p>§. 88. Thirdly, ponder and meditate ſeriouſly on <hi>Gods</hi> ineſtimable love towards us, who hath nor ſpared to give his onely beloved Sonne out of his boſome to dye for us, and to purchaſe thereby every good thing we doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy either for ſoule or body, even to the leaſt bit of bread we eat; and this will make thee (if thou haſt any ingenuity) to direct all thy thoughts, ſpeeches, and actions to his glory, as he hath directed thy eternall ſalvation thereunto, and often force thee to breake out into this or the like expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, What ſhall I render unto thee O Lord for all thy benefits? but love thee my Creator, and become a new creature.</p>
               <p>§. 89. Fourthly, conſider that the Lord beholdeth thee in all places, and in every thing thou doſt; even as the eyes of a well drawne Picture are faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on thee which way ſoever thou turneſt; yea, conſider him as a juſt Judge, who will not let ſinne goe unpuniſhed, and this will make thee keep a narrower watch over thy very thoughts then any other can doe over thine actions.</p>
               <p>§. 90. Fifthly, if thou wilt be ſafe from evill workes avoyd the occaſions at leaſt if thou wilt keep thy ſelfe from iniquity, have no fellowſhip with the workers of iniquity, for it is not more hard to finde vertue in evill company then to miſſe vice; <hi>They were mingled among the Heathen</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) and what followes, <hi>they learned their workes,</hi> Pſal. 106.35. yea, how ſoone was <hi>Peter</hi> changed, with but comming into the High Prieſts Hall; and the like with <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> which made <hi>David</hi> to ſay ſo ſoone as he had conſidered it, <hi>Depart from me all ye workers of iniquity, for I will keepe the Commandements of my God,</hi> Pſal. 119.115. knowing that he could not doe the one without the other. And indeed, the choiſe of a mans company is one of the moſt weighty actions of our lives, for our future well or ill being depends on that election, and many a man had been good that is not if he had but kept good company.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119873:27"/>
               <p>§. 91. Sixthly and laſtly, but chiefly and principally, omit not to pray for the aſſiſtance of Gods ſpirit, otherwiſe thy ſtrength is ſmall; yea, except <hi>God</hi> give thee repentance, and removes all impediments that may hinder, thou canſt no more turne thy ſelfe then thou couldeſt at firſt make thy ſelfe; <hi>We are not ſufficient of our ſelves to thinke,</hi> much leſſe to ſpeake, leaſt of all to doe <hi>that which is good,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.5. John 15.4, 5. we are ſwift to all evill but to any good immoveable; wherefore beg of <hi>God,</hi> that he will give you a' new heart, and when the heart is changed all the members will follow after it, as the reſt of the Creatures after the <hi>Sunne</hi> when it ariſeth; importune him for grace, that thou mayeſt firmely reſolve; ſpeedily begin, and continually perſevere in doing, and ſuffering his holy Will; deſire him to informe and reforme thee ſo, that thou mayeſt neither misbeleeve nor miſ-live; to rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate thy heart, change and purifie thy nature, ſubdue thy reaſon, rectifie thy judgement, reforme and ſtrengthen thy will, renew thy affections, and beat downe in thee whatſoever ſtands in oppoſition to the Scepter of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> not forgetting that prayer is the key of Heaven, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calls it.</p>
               <p>And now for concluſion, if thou receiveſt any power againſt thy corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons forget not to be thankfull, and when <hi>God</hi> hath the fruit of his mercies he will not ſpare to ſow much where he reapes much. Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord give you underſtanding to ſtrive after thoſe graces wherewith <hi>a true Beleever</hi> is quallified; and whereof I have given you a Copy in the fore going Character.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>Adde this Character of <hi>A true Beleever,</hi> as an appendix to <hi>The Cure of Miſpriſion.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
